[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]
DAVID MALAN: All right, one last time.
大卫·马兰：好的，最后一次。
This is CS50, and we realize this has been a bit of a fire hose
这是CS50，我们意识到这有点像消防水管
over the past-- thank you.
在过去的——谢谢。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
Thank you.
谢谢。
We realize this has been a bit of a fire hose.
我们意识到这有点像消防水管。
Indeed, recall that we began the class in week 0,
确实，还记得我们在第0周开始这门课程，
months ago with this here MIT hack, wherein
几个月前，我们用这个MIT的黑客行为，其中
a fire hose was connected to a fire hydrant,
一根消防水管连接到消防栓上，
in turn connected to a water fountain.
然后连接到一个饮水机上。
And it really spoke to just how much information
这确实说明了我们预计在过去几个月里会有多少信息
we predicted would be sort of flowing at you over the past few months.
流向你。
If you are feeling all these weeks later that it never actually
如果你在几周后感觉它从未真正
got easy, and with pset 1 to pset 2, pset 3 on to pset 9,
变得容易，从Pset 1到Pset 2，从Pset 3到Pset 9，
you never quite felt like you got your footing,
你从未真正感觉到你找到了自己的立足点，
realize that it's kind of by design because every time you did get your--
意识到这是一种设计，因为每次你真的找到了自己的——
every time you did get your footing, our goal
每次你真的找到立足点，我们的目标
was to ratchet things up a little bit more
就是要把事情提升一点
so that you feel like you're still getting
这样你就会感觉你仍然在获得
something out of that final week.
那一周的收获。
And indeed, that final week is now behind us.
确实，那一周已经过去了。
All that remains ahead of us is the final project.
我们面前剩下的就是最后的项目。
And what we thought we'd do today is recap a little bit of where we began
我们今天想做的是回顾一下我们从哪里开始
and where you hopefully now are.
以及你现在应该到达的地方。
Take a look at the world of cybersecurity,
看看网络安全的世界，
because it's a scary place out there, but hopefully you're
因为那里很危险，但希望你已经
all the more equipped now with a mental model
更有能力，现在你拥有一个思维模型
and vocabulary to evaluate threats in the real world, and as educated people,
和词汇来评估现实世界中的威胁，作为受过教育的人，
make decisions, be it in industry, be it in government,
做出决定，无论是在工业界，还是在政府部门，
be it in your own personal or professional lives.
还是在你自己的个人或职业生活中。
And we hope ultimately, too, that you've walked away
我们希望最终，你也带走了
with a very practical skill, including how
一项非常实用的技能，包括如何
to program in C, how to program in Python,
用C语言编程，用Python语言编程，
how to program in SQL, how to program in JavaScript
用SQL编程，用JavaScript编程
in the context, for instance, of even more HTML, CSS, and the like.
例如，在更多HTML、CSS等方面的背景下。
But most importantly, we hope that you've really walked away
但最重要的是，我们希望你真正带走了
with an understanding of how to program.
对编程的理解。
Like, you're not going to have CS50 by your side or even the duck by your side
就像，你不会一直带着CS50或者鸭子
forever.
陪伴在你身边。
You're going to have really, that foundation that hopefully you'll
你将真正拥有，那个希望你能
walk out of here today having accumulated over the past few months.
今天离开这里时拥有的基础，它是在过去的几个月里积累起来的。
And even though the world's languages are going to change,
即使世界上的语言会发生变化，
new technologies are going to exist tomorrow, hopefully,
新的技术将在明天出现，希望
you'll find that a lot of the foundations
你会发现，很多基础
over the past several months really do stay with you
在过去的几个月里，真的会留存在你身上
and allow you to bootstrap to a new understanding,
让你可以快速掌握新的知识，
even if you never take another CS course again.
即使你再也不上任何CS课程了。
Ultimately, we claim that this was all about solving problems.
最终，我们声称这一切都是关于解决问题的。
And hopefully, we've kind of cleaned up your thinking a little bit,
希望我们稍微整理了一下你的思路，
given you more tools in your toolkit to think and evaluate and solve
给了你更多工具，让你能够更系统地思考、评估和解决
problems more methodically, not only in code, but just algorithmically as well.
问题，不仅是在代码中，而且在算法上也是如此。
And keep this mind too.
还有要记住这一点。
If you're still feeling like, oh, I never really quite got your footing--
如果你仍然感觉，哦，我从未真正找到自己的立足点——
my footing, think back to how hard Mario might have felt some three months ago.
我的立足点，回想一下三个月前马里奥可能会有多难。
But what ultimately matters in this course is indeed, not so much
但在这门课中，真正重要的是，不是说
where you end up relative to your classmates,
你最终与同学相比处于什么位置，
but where you end up relative to yourself when you began.
而是你最终与自己开始时的状态相比处于什么位置。
So here we are, and consider that there delta.
所以我们现在就在这里，想想那之间的差距。
And if you don't believe me, like, literally go back this weekend
如果你不相信我，就像，真的去这个周末
or sometime soon, try implementing Mario in C. And I do
或者尽快，尝试用C语言实现马里奥。我确实
dare say it's going to come a little more readily to you.
敢说你更容易做到。
Even if you need to Google something, ask the duck something,
即使你需要谷歌一些东西，问鸭子一些东西，
ask ChatGPT something just to remember some stupid syntactic detail,
问ChatGPT一些东西，只是为了记住一些愚蠢的语法细节，
the ideas hopefully are with you now for some time.
这些想法现在应该会陪伴你一段时间。
So that there hack is actually fully documented here in MIT.
所以，那个黑客行为实际上在MIT这里有完整的记录。
Our friends down the road have a tradition
我们路边的朋友有一个传统
of doing such things every year.
每年都会做这些事。
One year, one of my favorites was they turned the dome of MIT
有一年，我最喜欢的其中一件是，他们把MIT的圆顶
into a recreation of R2-D2.
变成了R2-D2的复制品。
So there's a rich history of going to great lengths to prank each other,
所以，他们为了恶作剧彼此，有着悠久的历史，
or even us here Harvard folks akin to the Harvard Yale video
或者就像我们哈佛的人一样，类似于上一次我们看过的哈佛耶鲁视频
we took a look at last time.
我们上一次看过的那个。
And this duck has really become a defining characteristic
而这只鸭子，真的成为
of late of CS50, so much so that last year, the CS50 Hackathon, we invited
CS50的典型特征，以至于去年，在CS50黑客马拉松上，我们邀请了
the duck along.
那只鸭子。
It posed, as it is here, for photographs with your classmates past.
它摆姿势，就像现在这样，和过去的同学们一起拍照。
And then around like, 4:00 AM, it disappeared, and the duck went missing.
然后，大约凌晨4点，它消失了，鸭子不见了。
And we were about to head off to IHOP, our friends from Yale.
我们正要出发去IHOP，我们耶鲁的朋友们。
Your former classmates had just kind of packed up
你们以前的同学们刚收拾好东西
and started driving back to New haven.
开始开车返回纽黑文。
And I'm ashamed to say our first thought was that Yale took it.
我不好意思地说，我们首先想到的是耶鲁拿走了它。
And we texted our TA friends on the shuttle buses, 4:30 AM asking, hey,
我们给班上的助教朋友们发了短信，凌晨4:30，问，嘿，
did you take our duck because we kind of need it next week for the CS50 fair?
你们拿走了我们的鸭子吗？因为下周的CS50博览会我们需要它。
And I'm ashamed to say that we thought so, but it was not in fact, them.
我不好意思地说，我们当时确实这么认为，但事实并非如此。
It was this guy instead, down the road.
而是这个家伙，在路边。
Because a few hours later after I think, no sleep on much of our part,
因为几个小时后，我想我们大部分人几乎没睡，
we got the equivalent of a ransom email.
我们收到了相当于勒索邮件的东西。
"Hi, David, it's your friend, bbd.
“嗨，大卫，我是你的朋友，bbd。
I hope you're well and not too worried after I left so abruptly
我希望你一切安好，不要太担心我昨天晚上那么突然地离开，
yesterday night after such a successful Hackathon and semester so far.
昨天晚上，在这么成功的黑客马拉松和本学期的课程结束后。
I just needed to unwind a bit and take a trip to new places and fresh air.
我只是需要放松一下，去一些新地方，呼吸新鲜空气。
Don't worry though, I will return safe, sound, healthy, home
别担心，我会安全、健康地回家，
once I am more relaxed.
等我能放松下来了。
As of right now, I'm just spending some few days with our tech friends
现在我正和我们技术朋友们待在一起，
up Massachusetts Avenue.
在马萨诸塞大街上。
They gave me a hand on moving tonight.
他们今晚帮我搬家。
For some reason, I could never find my feet, and they've been amazing hosts.
由于某些原因，我总是找不到方向，而他们一直是最好的主人。
I will see you soon and I will miss you and Harvard specially our students.
我很快就会见到你，我会想念你，以及哈佛，尤其是我们的学生。
Sincerely yours, CS50 bbd."
你的，CS50 bbd。"
So almost a perfect hack.
所以几乎是一个完美的黑客攻击。
They didn't quite get the DDB detail quite right.
他们没有完全正确地理解 DDB 的细节。
But after this, they proceeded to make a scavenger hunt of sorts of clues here.
但在这之后，他们开始在这里进行某种形式的寻宝游戏。
This here is Hundredville.
这里就是百村。
And so in Hundredville, they handed out flyers to students at MIT,
所以，他们在百村向 MIT 的学生发放传单，
inviting folks to write a Python program to solve a mystery.
邀请人们写一个 Python 程序来解开一个谜团。
"The CS50 duck has been stolen.
“CS50 的鸭子被偷了，
The town of Hundredville has been called on you
百村呼吁你
to solve the mystery of the-- authorities
来解开这个谜团——当局
believe that the thief stole the duck and then shortly thereafter took
认为小偷偷了鸭子，然后不久后就带走了
a walk out of town.
这鸭子离开了小镇。
Your goal is to identify who the thief is, what school the thief escaped to,
你的目标是找到小偷是谁，小偷逃到了哪所学校，
and who the thief's accomplice is who helped them escape.
以及谁是小偷的同伙，帮助他们逃脱。
This took place on December 2, 2022, and took place at the CS50 Hackathon."
这件事发生在 2022 年 12 月 2 日，发生在 CS50 黑客马拉松上。”
In the days to come, we proceeded to receive a series of ransom postcards
在接下来的日子里，我们陆续收到了一系列赎金明信片，
as the duck traveled, not only to MIT to Professor John Guttag 6.100B class,
当这只鸭子四处旅行时，不仅去到了 MIT 的 John Guttag 教授的 6.100B 课程，
which is a rough equivalent of CS50 down the road.
这门课程相当于 CS50 的一个简化版本。
Pictured there our CS50 duck with some tape on its torso.
照片中是我们的 CS50 鸭子，它的躯干上贴着一些胶带。
But then the duck took, apparently, a ride,
但后来这只鸭子显然坐了一趟车，
either in actuality or with Photoshop, not only there,
无论是在现实中还是用 Photoshop，不仅在那里，
took a tour of the Charles River in front of Harvard,
它在哈佛大学前的查尔斯河上游览了一番，
the Charles in front of Boston.
还有波士顿前的查尔斯河。
It went all the way over to Yale.
它一直走到耶鲁大学。
We then received this postcard from Princeton
然后我们收到了来自普林斯顿的明信片，
all the way over from Stanford.
还有来自斯坦福的。
Duck took a flight according to this photo here,
根据这张照片，这只鸭子还飞了一趟，
and then saw a bit of the world as well.
还看到了世界的一部分。
So eventually, we received a follow-up email saying, "Hi, David.
所以最后，我们收到了这样一封邮件：“嗨，大卫。
I intend to arrive for the fair between 8:37 AM and 9:47 AM.
我打算在上午 8:37 到 9:47 之间到达展会。
It would be easier for my MIT hacker friends to bring me to the right
如果有人在那里举着写着“鸭子”的牌子，我的 MIT 黑客朋友们更容易把我带到正确的地方
location if there's someone waiting there with a sign that says 'Duck'."
如果有人在那里举着写着“鸭子”的牌子。”
I'm not sure if we actually stood there with a sign holding duck,
我不确定我们是否真的在那里拿着写着“鸭子”的牌子站着，
but it turns out they came actually earlier in the morning
但事实证明，他们实际上是在早上早些时候来的
to escape detection altogether.
为了完全避免被发现。
The duck found its home and everyone lived happily ever after.
这只鸭子找到了它的家，从此大家幸福地生活在一起。
And here the duck is again today.
而这只鸭子今天又回来了。
But our props to our friends down the road at MIT
但我们感谢 MIT 的朋友们
for returning the duck safely and for going to such crazy lengths
安全地归还了这只鸭子，并且付出了如此多的努力
to put us in the annals of MIT's Hacks Gallery.
把我们列入 MIT 黑客画廊的史册。
In fact, in exchange for this, we sent them a little package.
事实上，作为交换，我们给他们送了一个小包裹。
And without telling you what it is, you can read more
没有告诉你是什么，你可以阅读更多
about this here hack that's now been immortalized
关于这个现在已经不朽的 hack
on hacks.mit.edu at this URL here.
在 hacks.mit.edu 上，这个 URL 就在这里。
So maybe round of applause for our friends
所以，让我们为我们的朋友们鼓掌吧
down the road for having pulled that off a year ago.
感谢他们一年前做到了这一点。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
So before we dive into some of today's material,
所以在我们深入研究今天的一些材料之前，
I wanted to give you a sense of what lies ahead as well.
我想让你了解一下未来会发生什么。
So this year's CS50 Hackathon is an annual tradition,
所以今年的 CS50 黑客马拉松是一个年度传统，
whereby students here at Harvard and our friends from Yale who
哈佛的学生以及来自耶鲁的朋友们
will take buses in the other direction to join us
将乘坐公共汽车从另一个方向过来，加入我们
in about a week's time for an epic all-nighter, starting roughly at 7:00
大约一周后，我们将举行一个史诗般的通宵活动，大约从晚上 7:00 开始
PM ending roughly at 7:00 AM will be punctuated
晚上 7:00 结束，期间将穿插
by multiple meals, first meal-- first dinner around 9:00 PM, second dinner
多餐，第一餐——第一顿晚餐在晚上 9:00 左右，第二顿晚餐
around 1:00 AM.
在凌晨 1:00 左右。
And those of you who still have the energy
而那些仍然精力充沛的同学
and are still awake around 5:00 AM, we'll hop in a shuttle bus
仍然在凌晨 5:00 左右醒着的，我们将乘坐班车
and head down to IHOP, the larger one down the road,
前往 IHOP，也就是路上的那个较大的 IHOP，
not the one in the square, and have a little bit of breakfast together.
不是广场上的那个，一起吃点早餐。
The evening typically begins a little bit
晚上通常会这样开始，充满活力，重点是
like this with a lot of energy, the focus of which
充满活力，重点是
is entirely on final projects.
最终项目。
The staff will be present, but the intent
工作人员会到场，但目的
is not to be 12 hours of office hours.
不是连续 12 个小时的办公时间。
Indeed, the staff will be working on their own projects or psets,
事实上，工作人员将忙于自己的项目或作业，
final projects, and the like, but to guide you toward and point you
最终项目等等，但目的是引导你，指引你
in the direction of solutions to new problems you have.
找到解决你遇到的新问题的方案。
And we do think that the duck, and in turn, AI, CS50.ai and other tools
我们认为这只鸭子，以及由此带来的 AI、CS50.ai 和其他工具
you'll now be able to use, including the actual ChatGPT, the actual GitHub
你将可以使用，包括实际的 ChatGPT、实际的 GitHub
Copilot, or other AI tools which are now reasonable to use
Copilot 或其他现在可以用合理的 AI 工具
at this point in the semester as you off board from CS50
在本学期这个时候，当你离开 CS50 时
and enter the real world.
进入现实世界。
Should be an opportunity for you to take your newfound knowledge of software
这将是一个机会，让你运用你新学到的软件知识
out for a spin and build something of your very own, something
来实际操作，并创建属于你自己的东西，一些
that even maybe the TFs and myself have never dabbled in before,
甚至可能是助教和我都从未尝试过的事情，
but with all of this now software support by your side.
但现在有了这些软件支持，在你身边。
This here is our very own CS50 shuttles that will take us then to IHOP.
这是我们自己的 CS50 班车，会把我们送到 IHOP。
And then a week after that is the epic CS50
然后在一周后，就是史诗般的 CS50
fair, which will be an opportunity to showcase what it is you'll
展会，将是一个展示你将在接下来的几周内完成的作品的机会，面向学生、教师和
pull off over the next few weeks to students, faculty,
面向学生、教师和
and staff across campus.
校园里的工作人员。
More details to come, but you'll bring over your laptop or phone
更多细节待公布，但你需要带你的笔记本电脑或手机
to a large space on campus.
到校园里的一个大空间。
We'll invite all of your friends, even family if they're around.
我们将邀请你所有的朋友，甚至你的家人，如果他们就在附近。
And the goal will be simply to have chats like this
目标就是像这样简单地聊天
and present your final project to passersby.
然后向路人展示你们的最终项目。
There'll be a bit of an incentive model, whereby
我们还将设置一个激励机制，
anyone who chats you up about their project,
任何和你聊他们项目的人，
you can give a little sticker to.
你都可以给一个小贴纸。
And that will enter them into a raffle for fabulous prizes
这将使他们有机会参加抽奖，赢得丰厚的奖品
to grease the wheels of conversations as well.
来推动对话的进行。
And you'll see faculty from across campus join us as well.
你还会看到来自校园各地的教职工也加入我们。
But ultimately, you walk out of that event with this here CS50 shirt,
但最终，你离开活动时会得到这件CS50 T恤，
one like it, so you too, can proudly proclaim that you indeed took CS50.
和它一样的，这样你也可以自豪地宣称你确实上了CS50。
So all that and more to come, resting on finally, those final projects.
所以这一切，以及更多，都将建立在最终的项目上。
But how to get there.
但如何才能做到呢？
So here are some general advice that's not necessarily going
以下是一些通用的建议，它们不一定会适用于所有最终项目。
to be applicable to all final projects.
但随着我们走出CS50，进入现实世界，
But as we exit CS50 and enter the real world,
以下是一些关于你可能阅读、下载的内容的建议，
here are some tips on what you might read, what you might download,
一些起点，这样你就能回答常见问题，即“现在怎么办？”
sort of starting points so that in answer to the FAQ, what now?
例如，如果你想在自己的Mac或PC上体验
So for instance, if you would like to begin
更多使用cs50.dev提供的云端编程环境，
to experience on your own Mac or PC more of the programming environment
你可以安装一些命令行工具到你的笔记本电脑、台式机上，
that we provided to you, sort of turnkey style in the cloud using cs50.dev,
或者类似的设备。
you can actually install command line tools on your own laptop, desktop,
例如，苹果有他们自己的。
or the like.
Windows也有他们自己的。
For instance, Apple has their own.
所以你可以在自己的电脑上打开一个终端窗口
Windows has their own.
并在其中执行你在Linux中使用过的许多命令。
So you can open a terminal window on your own computer
整个学期都是这样。
and execute much of the same commands that you've been doing in Linux
学习Git，Git是一种版本控制软件。
this whole term.
它在业界非常流行。
Learning Git, so Git is version control software.
它是一种保存文件多个版本的机制。
And it's very, very popular in industry.
现在，如果你还使用
And it's a mechanism for saving multiple versions of your files.
在你的Mac或PC上，甚至使用文件名，
Now, this is something you might be familiar with if still,
你可能就熟悉这种机制了，比如简历版本1、简历版本2、
even using file names in the real world, like on your Mac or PC--
周一晚上版本、周二版本，等等。
maybe this is resume version 1, resume version 2,
如果你使用的是谷歌文档，现在这种情况会自动发生。
resume Monday night version, resume Tuesday, or whatever the case may be.
但对于代码来说，它可以自动发生，也可以
If you're using Google documents, this happens automatically nowadays.
使用这种工具更系统地进行。
But with code, it can happen automatically, but also
Git是一个非常流行的工具，它可以与他人进行协作。
more methodically using this here tool.
你实际上一直在暗中使用它，
And Git is a very popular tool for collaborating with others as well.
在CS50的许多工具背后。
And you've actually been secretly using it
但我们隐藏了一些细节。
underneath the hood for a lot of CS50's tools.
但布莱恩通过这个视频和其他一些参考资料，
But we've abstracted away some of the details.
可以剥开抽象，向你展示如何手动使用它。
But Brian, via this video and any number of other references,
你不再需要使用cs50.dev，但你仍然可以使用。
can peel back that abstraction and show you how to use it more manually.
你可以在自己的Mac或PC上安装VS Code。
You don't need to use cs50.dev anymore but you are welcome to.
如果你访问这里第一个网址，它是一个免费下载。
You can instead install VS Code onto your own Mac or PC.
它实际上是开源的。
If you go to this first URL here, it's a free download.
所以你甚至可以深入了解它本身是如何构建的。
It's actually open source.
在CS50自己的文档中，我们提供了一些提示，
So you can even poke around and see how it, itself is built.
可以让你看起来像CS50的环境，即使从长远来看，
And at CS50's own documentation, we have some tips
你想要完全断开连接。
for making it look like CS50's environment even if longer term,
你现在能做什么呢？
you want to cut the cord entirely.
你们中的许多人会
What can you now do?
在最终项目中处理网站，
Well, many of you for your final projects
建立在问题集9、CS50金融和类似内容的基础上，
will typically tackle websites, sort of building on the ideas of problem
或者一般来说是动态的。
set 9, CS50 finance and the like, or just generally something dynamic.
但如果你想托管一个投资组合，比如你的简历，
But if you instead want to host a portfolio, like just your resume, just
你所完成的项目等等，静态网站
projects you've worked on and the like, a static websites
可以通过各种服务免费托管。
can be hosted for free via various services.
一个流行的服务是这里这个网址，叫做GitHub pages。
A popular one is this URL here, called GitHub pages.
还有一个提供免费层级服务的平台叫做
There's another service that offers a free tier called
Netlify，它可以让你免费静态托管自己的项目。
Netlify that can allow you to host your own projects statically for free.
但当涉及到更动态的托管时，你会有更多选择。
But when it comes to more dynamic hosting, you have many more options.
这些只是一些最受欢迎的选择。
And these are just some of the most popular.
前三个是当今最大的云提供商，
The first three are some of the biggest cloud providers
无论是亚马逊、微软Azure还是谷歌服务。
nowadays, whether it's Amazon or Microsoft Azure or Google services.
如果你访问这里第四个网址，它是GitHub的教育包，
If you go to this fourth URL here, this is GitHub's education pack,
他们与许多不同的公司合作，
they essentially broker with lots of different companies
为学生提供
to give students, specifically, discounts on
或免费使用许多工具。
or free access to a lot of tools.
所以你可能想在你有资格的时候注册它。
So you might want to sign up for that while you're eligible.
最后，这里还有两个其他流行的第三方服务，它们不是
And then lastly, here are two other popular third-party, but not
免费的，但非常普遍
free services, but that are very commonly
在你想要托管实际的web应用程序时使用。
used when you want to host actual web applications.
所以可能是Flask，也可能是其他东西，但它涉及到
So maybe it's Flask, maybe it's something else, but something
一些输入和输出。
that involves some input and output.
与此同时，问题是——有很多社区。
Questions meanwhile-- so there's just lots of communities.
如果你想关注科技领域的最新动态，
If you want to keep an eye on what's happening in tech,
这些只是一些受欢迎的选择。
these are just some of the popular options.
毫无疑问，如果你有一些科技爱好者朋友，
And undoubtedly, if you have some techie friends,
他们也会有一些建议。
they'll have suggestions as well.
你可能会发现这些地方很有趣。
But you might find some of these destinations of interest.
当然，越来越多的人会向软件本身提问，
Of course increasingly, will you just ask questions of software itself,
人工智能，无论是ChatGPT、GitHub Copilot还是其他。
AI, whether it's ChatGPT, GitHub Copilot, or the like.
然后是课程，我们显然对屏幕上显示的内容有些偏见。
And then classes, we're clearly a little biased here with what's on the screen.
所以这些课程不是大学课程本身，而是CS50团队
So these aren't college classes per se, but freely available OpenCourseWare
随着时间的推移，整理的免费开放式课程。
courses that CS50's team has put together over time.
简而言之，正如你从这些网址的后缀中可以推断的那样，
And in a nutshell as you can infer from the suffix of each of these URLs,
如果你想了解更多关于Python的信息，CS50
if you want to learn more about Python, CS50
有一个免费的在线公开课，或者关于SQL，感谢
has got a free, open online class for that, or SQL, thanks
卡特，还有关于web和人工智能的东西，感谢布莱恩，还有一门游戏课程，感谢科尔顿，
to Carter, web and AI stuff, thanks to Brian, a games class, thanks to Colton,
以及其他许多课程。
cybersecurity, which will extend where we leave off today.
网络安全，这将扩展我们今天结束的地方。
And then if you're more interested, not so
如果你更感兴趣，不是那么
much in coding and going more deeply into software,
对编码感兴趣，并且更深入地研究软件，
but want to take a step higher level and focus more on intersections of computer
但想更上一层楼，更多地关注计算机与
science with business or law or technology,
科学，商业，法律或技术的交叉点。
those two are freely available, if you're
这两个是免费的，如果你
looking for something to do over January the summer or just to dabble over time.
正在寻找一些在1月，夏季或只是偶尔做的事情。
And there's innumerable other free resources
还有无数其他免费的资源
from other folks on the internet as well certainly too.
当然还有来自互联网上其他人的资源。
All right, so a few invitations and thank yous.
好吧，所以有一些邀请和感谢。
So one, after today, after we dive into and out of cybersecurity,
所以，第一，在今天之后，在我们深入和离开网络安全之后，
please do stay in touch via any of CS50's online communities.
请通过 CS50 的任何在线社区保持联系。
As we start to recruit next year's team for teaching fellows, teaching
随着我们开始招募明年的教学研究员团队，教学
assistants, course assistants, we'll be in touch via email
助理，课程助理，我们会通过电子邮件与您联系
for those opportunities as well.
这些机会也是如此。
And now some thanks for the group before we then dive into here today's topic.
现在，在我们深入今天的主题之前，感谢一下大家。
So one, allow me to thank our hosts here for giving us
首先，请允许我感谢我们的主办方，他们为我们提供了
access to such a wonderful, privileged space to just hold classes in,
如此美妙的特权空间来上课，
the whole team for Memorial Hall.
整个纪念堂团队。
Our thanks too, to ESS, which is the team that makes everything sound so
我们也要感谢 ESS，这是让所有事物在这样的空间中听起来很棒的团队，包括音乐，麦克风等等，我们的朋友
good in spaces like this with music, mics, and the like, our friends,
当然还有路上的韦斯利在昌肖，我们这个学期每个星期五都会去那里。
of course, Wesley down the road at Changsho, where we went most
如果你从来没有去过，或者你是在线上听到的，
every other Friday this semester.
请加入我们在路上的 Mass Ave 上昌肖的演出。
If you've never actually been, or if you're hearing this online,
随时都可以。
please join our friends at Changsho show on Mass Ave down the road
特别是 CS50 团队 - 房间里有很多工作人员
any time you might like.
在房间里操作摄像头，包括这里和后面，以及在线上。
And then especially, CS50's team-- there's quite a few humans
感谢大家。
operating cameras in the room, both here and way in back, as well as online.
[鼓掌]
My thanks.
感谢他们让这一切看起来和听起来都很好。
[APPLAUSE]
你看不到的是，当我真正搞砸了的时候，
Thank you to them for making this look and sound so good.
即使我们没有实时修复它，他们也很乐意
And what you don't see is when I do actually screw up,
帮助我们回到过去，修复问题，这样你的继任者就能拥有一个更好的版本了。
even if we don't fix it in real time, they very kindly
还有 CS50 的索菲·安德森，
help us go back in time, fix things, so that your successors have hopefully,
她是 CS50 教学研究员之一的女儿，
an even improved version as well.
住在新西兰，她以动画形式将 CS50 的鸭子带入了生活。
And then as well, CS50's own Sophie Anderson,
感谢索菲，这只鸭子现在无处不在，包括最近
who is the daughter of one of CS50's teaching fellows
出现在一些 T 恤上。
who lives all the way over in New Zealand, who has wonderfully
当然，我们有这个庞大的支持结构，
brought the CS50 duck to life in this animated form.
以团队的形式。
thanks to Sophie, this duck is now everywhere, including most recently,
这是我们一些过去的团队成员，但他们
on some T-shirts too.
在第七周通过 Zoom 向我们展示了 TCP/IP 的工作原理。
But of course, we have this massive support structure
他们通过传递信封来展示。
in the form of the team.
我当时评论说，免责声明，这实际上需要我们付出
This is some of our past team members, but who
很多努力。
wonderfully via Zoom you'll recall in week seven,
所以我认为我会分享我们整个教学团队的代表性感谢，
showed us how TCP/IP works by passing those envelopes up,
无论是卡特、茱莉亚、奥赞、科迪
down, left, and right.
以及所有在剑桥和新海的 C50 团队成员，
I commented at the time, disclaim, that it actually took us
我想让你看看幕后的事情是如何进行的。
quite a bit of effort to do that.
你看不到的幕后情况。
And so I thought I would share as a representative thanks
所以让我切换到这边并播放。
of our whole teaching team, whether it's Carter and Julia and Ozan and Cody
[视频播放]
and all of C50's team members in Cambridge in New Hey,
[听不见]
thought I'd give you a look behind the scenes at how things go indeed,
[听不见] 缓冲。
behind the scenes that you don't necessarily see.
好的。
So let me switch over here and hit play.
乔希？
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
不错。
[INAUDIBLE]
海伦？
[INAUDIBLE] Buffering.
哦。
OK.
[笑]
Josh?
[听不见] 莫尼 - 不，哦，等等。
Nice.
太棒了，乔希。
Helen?
索菲。
Oh.
太棒了。
[CHUCKLING]
太完美了。
[INAUDIBLE] Moni-- no, oh, wait.
莫尼。
That was amazing, Josh.
[笑] 我想我 -
Sophie.
[插话的声音]
Amazing.
轮到你了，[听不见]。
That was perfect.
盖伊。
Moni.
太棒了。
[LAUGHTER] I think I--
谢谢大家。
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
太好了。
- Over to you, [INAUDIBLE].
[播放结束]
Guy.
好的，这些片段除外，
That was amazing.
感谢整个教学团队让这堂课成为可能。
Thank you all.
[鼓掌]
- So good.
所以，网络安全是指
[END PLAYBACK]
保护我们的系统、数据、帐户等的流程。
DAVID MALAN: All right, these outtakes aside,
而且它越来越重要，因为它
my thanks to the whole teaching team for making this whole class possible.
已经存在，仅仅是因为技术无处不在，
[APPLAUSE]
在我们的桌子上，我们的腿上，我们的口袋里，以及其他地方。
So cybersecurity, this refers to the process
那么到底是什么呢？
of keeping secure our systems, our data, our accounts, and.
我们如何作为过去几周的计算机科学学生，
More and it's something that's going to be increasingly important, as it
更深入地思考问题，更仔细地思考问题，
already is, just because of the sheer omnipresence of technology
或许甚至对我们的直觉进行量化，我想你们很多人
on our desks, on our laps, in our pockets, and beyond.
在决定时都会有这种直觉，某件事是安全的还是不安全的？
So exactly what is it?
首先，安全意味着什么？
And how can we, as students of computer science over the past many weeks,
作为世界公民，你们现在如何回答这个问题？
think about things a little more methodically, a little more carefully,
安全意味着什么？
and maybe even put some numbers to the intuition that I think a lot of you
观众：抵御攻击。
probably have when it comes to deciding, is something secure or is it not?
好的，所以抵御攻击，我喜欢这个说法。
So first of all, what does it mean for something to be secure?
关于安全含义的其他想法？
How might you as citizens of the world now answer that question?
这是什么意思？
What does it mean to be secure?
是的。
AUDIENCE: Resistant to attack.
观众：你控制谁有权访问它。
DAVID MALAN: OK, so resistant to attack, I like that formulation.
好的，所以抵御攻击，我喜欢这个说法。
Other thoughts on what it means to be secure?
关于安全含义的其他想法？
What does it mean?
这是什么意思？
Yeah.
是的。
AUDIENCE: You control who has access to it.
观众：你控制谁有权访问它。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so you control who has access to something.
是的，所以你可以控制谁可以访问某些东西。
And there's these techniques known as authentication, like logging in,
这些技术被称为身份验证，就像登录一样，
authorization, deciding whether or not that person,
授权，决定那个人是否
once authenticated, should have access to things.
在经过身份验证后，应该有权访问这些东西。
And, of course, you and I are very commonly
当然，你我非常普遍地
in the habit of using fairly primitive mechanisms still.
习惯使用相当原始的机制。
Although, we'll touch today on some technologies
虽然，我们今天会涉及一些技术
that we'll see all the more of in the weeks and months and years to come.
我们将在未来几周、几个月和几年中越来越多地看到这些技术。
But you and I are pretty much in the habit
但你我都有这样的习惯
of relying on passwords for most everything still today.
在今天，我们几乎依靠密码来完成大部分事情。
And so we thought we'd begin with exactly this topic
所以我们认为我们可以从这个主题开始
to consider just how secure or insecure is this mechanism and why
来思考这种机制究竟有多安全或不安全，以及为什么
and see if we can't evaluate it a little more
并看看我们是否可以对它进行更深入的评估
methodically so that we can make more than intuitive arguments,
有条理地，以便我们能提出更多直观的论据，
but quantitative compelling arguments as well.
而是令人信服的定量论据。
So unfortunately we humans are not so good at choosing passwords.
不幸的是，人类不太擅长选择密码。
And every year, accounts are hacked into.
而且每年都有账户被黑。
Maybe yours, maybe your friends, maybe your family members
可能是你的，可能是你的朋友，可能是你的家人
have experienced this already.
已经经历过这样的事情。
And this unfortunately happens to so many people online.
不幸的是，这种情况发生在网上很多人的身上。
But, fortunately, there are security researchers
但幸运的是，世界上有安全研究人员
in the world that take a look at attacks once they have happened,
在攻击发生后，会对攻击进行调查，
particularly when data from attacks, databases, are posted online
特别是当攻击数据、数据库发布到网上时
or on the so-called dark web or the like and downloaded
或者在所谓的暗网上发布，或者类似的被下载
by others for malicious purposes, they can also conversely provide us
被其他人用于恶意目的，他们也可以反过来为我们提供
with some insights as to the behavior of us humans
关于人类行为的一些见解
that might give us some insights as to when and why things
这可能会给我们一些关于什么时候以及为什么这些事情
are getting attacked successfully.
被成功攻击的见解。
So as of last year, here, for instance, according to one measure
截至去年，例如，根据一项指标
are the top 10 most popular, a.k.a.
是前 10 个最流行的，也就是
worst passwords-- at least according to the data
最糟糕的密码——至少根据数据
that security researchers have been able to glean--
安全研究人员能够收集到的数据——
by attacks that have already happened.
通过已经发生的攻击。
So the number one password as of last year, according to systems compromised,
所以根据被入侵的系统，去年最流行的密码是
was 123456.
123456。
The second most, admin.
第二名是 admin。
The third most, 12345678.
第三名是 12345678。
And thereafter, 123456789, 1234, 12345, password, 123, Aa123456, and then
然后是 123456789、1234、12345、password、123、Aa123456，以及
1234567890.
1234567890。
So you can actually infer--
所以你实际上可以推断——
sort of goofy as some of these are-- you can actually infer certain policies
虽然这些密码有些愚蠢——但你实际上可以推断出某些策略
from these, right?
从这些密码中推断出来，对吧？
The fact that we're taking such little effort to choose our password
我们选择密码付出的努力如此之少，这一事实
seems to correlate really with probably, what's
似乎确实与可能是什么相关联，
the minimum length of a password required for systems?
系统要求的密码的最小长度？
And you can see that at worst, some systems
你可以看到，最糟糕的情况是，一些系统
require only three digit passwords.
只需要三位数的密码。
And maybe they might require six or eight or nine or even 10.
可能它们需要六位数、八位数、九位数甚至十位数的密码。
But you can kind of infer corporate or policies from these passwords alone.
但你仅仅从这些密码就可以推断出公司或策略。
If you keep going through the list, there's some funnier ones even down
如果你继续浏览这个列表，你会发现有些更有趣的东西，即使在
the list that are nonetheless enlightening.
这个列表中，它们仍然很有启发性。
So, for instance, lower on the list is Iloveyou, no spaces.
例如，在这个列表的下方是 Iloveyou，没有空格。
Sort of adorable, maybe it's meaningful to you.
有点可爱，也许对你来说很有意义。
But if you can think of it, so can an adversary,
但如果你能想到它，攻击者也能想到它，
so can some hacker, so much so that it's this popular on these lists.
一些黑客也能想到它，以至于它在这些列表中如此受欢迎。
Qwertyuiop, it's not quite English, but its derivative of English keyboards.
Qwertyuiop，它不完全是英文，但它是英文键盘的衍生词。
Anyone?
有人知道吗？
Yeah, so this is, if you look at a US English keyboard,
是的，所以，如果你看一个美式英文键盘，
it's just the top row of keys if you just
它就是最上面的那一排键，如果你只是
hit them all together left or right to choose your, therefore, password.
把它们全部从左到右一起敲，从而选择你的密码。
And then this one, "password," which has an at
然后是这个，“password”，它用一个@
sign for the A and a zero for the O, which I guess I'm guessing some of you
符号代替 A，用 0 代替 O，我想我猜你们中有些人
do similar tricks.
也做过类似的把戏。
But this is the thing too, if you think like you're being clever,
但这也是重点，如果你认为自己很聪明，
well, there's a lot of other adversaries,
那么，有很多其他的攻击者，
there's a lot of adversaries out there who are just as good at being clever.
有很多攻击者也和你一样聪明。
So even heuristics like this that in the past, to be fair,
所以即使是这种启发式方法，公平地说，在过去，
you might have been taught to do because it confuses
你可能会被教导要这样做，因为它会迷惑
adversaries' or hackers' attempts, unfortunately, if you know to do it,
攻击者或黑客的尝试，不幸的是，如果你知道怎么做，
so does the adversary.
攻击者也知道怎么做。
And so your accounts aren't necessarily any more secure as a result.
所以你的账户不一定因此而更加安全。
So what are some of our takeaways from this?
那么，我们从中学到了什么？
Well, one, if you have these lists of passwords, all too possible
好吧，首先，如果你拥有这些密码列表，那么字典攻击就太有可能了
are, for instance, dictionary attacks.
例如，字典攻击。
Like we literally have published on the internet--
就像我们实际上已经发布在互联网上——
and there's a citation in the slides if you're curious--
如果你好奇的话，幻灯片中有一篇参考文献——
of these most popular passwords in the world.
这些世界上最流行的密码。
So what's a smart adversary going to do when trying to get into your account?
所以，一个聪明的攻击者在试图进入你的账户时会怎么做？
They're not necessarily going to try all possible passwords
他们不会尝试所有可能的密码
or try your birthday or things like that.
或者尝试你的生日之类的。
They're just going to start with this top 10 list, this top 100 list.
他们只会从这个前十名列表，这个前一百名列表开始。
And odds are, statistically, in a room this big,
而且，从统计学上来说，在一个这么大的房间里，
they're probably going to get into at least one person's account.
他们很可能至少会进入一个人的账户。
But let's consider maybe a little more academically what we can do about this.
但让我们从学术的角度考虑一下我们可以做些什么。
And let's start with something simple like the simplest, the most
让我们从简单的事情开始，比如最简单、最
omnipresent device we might all have now is some kind
普遍的设备，我们现在可能都拥有的一种
of mobile device like a phone.
移动设备，比如手机。
Generally speaking, Apple and Google and others
一般来说，苹果、谷歌和其他公司
are requiring of us that we at least have
要求我们至少拥有
a passcode or at least you're prompted to set it up
一个密码，或者至少会提示你设置它
even if you therefore opt out of it.
即使你因此选择退出。
But most of us probably have a passcode, be it numeric or alphabetic
但我们大多数人可能都有一个密码，无论是数字还是字母
or something else.
或者其他东西。
So what might we take away from that?
那么我们能从中学到什么？
Well, suppose that you do the bare minimum.
好吧，假设你只做最基本的事情。
And the default for years has generally been having
多年来，默认情况下，
at least four digits in your passcode.
你的密码至少要有四位数。
Well, what does that mean?
那么这意味着什么？
Well, how secure is that?
好吧，那有多安全？
How quickly might it be hacked?
它可能会被黑客攻击多快？
And, in fact, Carter, would you mind joining me up here?
事实上，卡特，你介意和我一起上来吗？
Perhaps we can actually decide together how best to proceed here.
也许我们可以一起决定在这里如何才能最好地进行。
If you want to flip over to your other screen there,
如果你想翻转到你的另一个屏幕，
we're going to ask everyone to go to--
我们要让每个人都去——
I'll pull it up here-- this URL here if you haven't already.
我将把它拉到此处——如果您还没有访问过，请访问此 URL。
And this is going to pull up a polling website that's
这将打开一个投票网站，
going to allow you in a moment to answer some multiple choice questions.
一会儿，它将允许您回答一些多项选择题。
This is the same URL as earlier if you already logged in.
如果您已经登录，则此 URL 与之前的 URL 相同。
And in just a moment, we're going to ask you a question.
一会儿，我们要问你一个问题。
And I think, can we show the question before we do this?
我想，我们可以在这样做之前显示问题吗？
Here's the first question from Carter here.
这是卡特提出的第一个问题。
How long might it take to crack--
破解一个四位数的密码可能需要多长时间？
that is, figure out-- a four-digit passcode on someone's phone,
也就是说，找出——手机上的四位数密码，
for instance?
例如？
How long might it take to crack a four-digit passcode?
破解一个四位数的密码可能需要多长时间？
Why don't we go ahead and flip over to see who is typing in what.
为什么我们不翻转过去看看谁在打什么。
And we'll see what the scores are already.
然后我们会看看分数是多少。
All right, and it looks like most of you think a few seconds.
好的，看起来大多数人认为几秒钟。
Some of you think a few minutes, a few hours, a few days.
有些人认为几分钟，几小时，几天。
So I'd say most of you are about to be very unpleasantly surprised.
所以我会说，大多数人将很快就会感到非常不愉快地惊讶。
In fact, the winner here is indeed going to be a few seconds,
事实上，这里获胜的将是几秒钟，
but perhaps even faster than that.
但可能比那还要快。
So, in fact, let me go ahead and do this.
所以，事实上，让我继续做这个。
Thank you to Carter.
谢谢卡特。
Let me flip over and let me introduce you
让我翻转过来，并向你介绍
to, unfortunately, what's a very real world problem known as a brute force
不幸的是，一个被称为暴力破解的现实世界问题。
attack.
攻击。
As the word kind of conjures, if you think
正如这个词所暗示的那样，如果你想到
to-- back to yesteryear when there was some kind of battering ram trying
到——回到过去，当时有一种攻城锤试图
to brute force their way into a castle door,
暴力破解进入城堡大门，
it just meant trying to hammer the heck out of a system.
它只是意味着试图猛烈地攻击系统。
A castle, in that case, to get into the destination.
在这种情况下，城堡，为了进入目的地。
Digitally though, this might mean being a little more clever.
但在数字世界中，这可能意味着更加聪明一些。
We all know how to write code in a bunch of different languages now.
我们现在都知道如何用多种不同的语言编写代码。
You could maybe open up a text editor, write a Python program to try all
你或许可以打开一个文本编辑器，编写一个 Python 程序，尝试所有
possible four-digit codes from 0000 to 9999 in order to figure out exactly,
可能的四位数代码，从 0000 到 9999，以便准确地找出，
how long does it actually take?
它实际上需要多长时间？
So let's first consider this.
所以让我们先考虑这一点。
Let me ask the next question.
让我问下一个问题。
How many four-digit passcodes are there?
有多少个四位数的密码？
Carter, if you wouldn't mind joining me and maybe just staying up
卡特，如果你不介意加入我，也许就留在这里
with me here to run our second question at this same URL.
和我一起在这里运行我们在这个相同 URL 上的第二个问题。
How many four-digit passcodes are there in the world?
世界上有多少个四位数的密码？
On your phone or laptop, you should now see the second question.
在你的手机或笔记本电脑上，你应该现在就能看到第二个问题。
And the answers include 4, 40, 9,999, 10,000, or it's OK to be unsure.
答案包括 4、40、9999、10000，或者不确定也可以。
Let's go ahead and flip over to the results.
让我们翻转到结果页面。
And it looks like most of you think 10,000.
看起来大多数人认为是 10000。
And, indeed, that is the case.
确实如此。
Because if I kind of led you with 0000 to 9999, that's 10,000 possibilities.
因为如果我引导你从 0000 到 9999，那就是 10000 种可能性。
So that is, in fact, a lot.
所以，事实上，这是一个很大的数字。
But most of you thought it'd take maybe a few seconds to actually brute force
但大多数人认为，实际上暴力破解可能只需要几秒钟。
your way into that.
破解进入它。
Let's consider how we might measure how long that actually takes.
让我们考虑一下如何测量实际需要多长时间。
So thank you.
谢谢。
So in the world of a four-digit passcode-- and they
所以，在四位数密码的世界中——它们
are, indeed, digits, decimal digits from 0 to 9--
确实是数字，从 0 到 9 的十进制数字——
another way to think about it is there's 10 possibilities for the first digit,
另一种思考方式是，第一个数字有 10 种可能性，
10 for the next, 10 to the 10.
下一个有 10 种，10 的 10 次方。
So that really gives us 10 times itself four times or 10,000 in total.
所以，这实际上给了我们 10 自乘四次，或者总共 10000。
But how long does that actually take?
但实际上需要多长时间？
Well, let me go ahead and do this.
好吧，让我继续做这个。
I'm going to go ahead and open up on my Mac here, not even--
我将继续在我的 Mac 上打开它，甚至不用——
not even Codespaces or cs50.dev today.
今天甚至不用 Codespaces 或 cs50.dev。
I'm going to open up VS Code itself.
我将打开 VS Code 本身。
So before class, I went ahead and installed VS Code on my own Mac here.
所以，在上课之前，我已经在我的 Mac 上安装了 VS Code。
It looks almost the same as Codespaces, though the windows
它看起来几乎和 Codespaces 一样，虽然窗口
might look a little different and the menus as well.
可能看起来有点不同，菜单也是一样。
And I've gone ahead here and begun a file called crack.py.
我在这里已经开始了一个名为 crack.py 的文件。
To crack something means to break into it,
破解某物意味着闯入它，
to figure out in this case what the passcode actually is.
在这种情况下，找出密码实际上是什么。
Well, how might I write some code to try all 10,000 possible passcodes?
好吧，我该如何编写代码来尝试所有 10000 种可能的密码？
And, heck, even though this isn't quite going
而且，哎呀，即使这并不完全是
to be like hacking into my actual phone, I
像黑进我的真实手机一样，我
bet I could find a USB or a lightning cable, connect the two devices,
我敢肯定我可以找到一根 USB 或 Lightning 数据线，连接这两个设备，
and maybe send all of these passcodes to my device trying to brute force
并将所有这些密码发送到我的设备，试图暴力破解
my way in.
我的方式。
And that's indeed how a hacker might go about doing this
而这正是黑客可能会采取的行动方式
if the manufacturer doesn't protect against that.
如果制造商没有防范这种情况。
So here's some code.
这是一些代码。
Let me go ahead and do this.
让我继续做这个。
From string, import digits.
从字符串中导入数字。
This isn't strictly necessary.
这不是严格必要的。
But in Python, there is a string library from which
但在 Python 中，有一个字符串库，你可以从中
you can get all of the decimal digits just so I don't
获取所有十进制数字，这样我就不必
have to manually type out 0 through 9.
手动输入 0 到 9。
But that's just a minor optimization.
但这只是一个小的优化。
But there's another library called itertools,
但还有一个名为 itertools 的库，
tools related to iteration, doing things in like a looping fashion, where
与迭代相关的工具，以循环的方式做事情，
I can import a cross product function, a function that's
我可以导入一个交叉乘积函数，一个能够
going to allow me to combine like all numbers with all numbers
让我将所有数字与所有数字组合起来的函数
again and again and again for the length of the passcode.
一遍又一遍，直到密码长度结束。
Now I can do a simple Python for loop like this.
现在我可以像这样写一个简单的Python循环。
For each passcode in the cross product of those 10 digits repeated four times.
对于那些重复四次的十个数字的交叉乘积中的每个密码。
In other words, this is just a programmatic Pythonic way
换句话说，这只是一个以编程方式用Python实现的
to implement the idea of combining all 10 digits with itself
将所有10位数字与自身组合的思想，
four times in a loop in this fashion.
用这种方式在循环中进行四次。
And just so we can visualize this, let's just go ahead
为了可视化，我们继续
and print out the passcode.
打印出密码。
But if I did have a lightning cable or a USB cable, I wouldn't print it.
但是，如果我有一个闪电线或USB线，我不会打印它。
I would maybe send it through the cable to the device
我可能会通过电缆将它发送到设备
to try to get through the passcode screen.
以尝试通过密码屏幕。
So we can revisit now the question of how long
现在我们可以重新审视这个问题，即需要多长时间
might it take to get into this device.
才能进入这个设备。
Well, let's just try this.
好吧，我们试一下。
Python of crack.py.
Python的crack.py。
And assume, again, it's connected via cable.
并且假设，再次，它是通过电缆连接的。
So we'll see how long this program takes to run and break into this here phone.
所以我们将看看这个程序运行并破解这个手机需要多长时间。
Done.
完成了。
So that's all it took for 10,000 iterations.
所以这只是10,000次迭代所需要的。
And this is on a Mac that's not even the fastest one out there.
这是在一台Mac上，它甚至不是最快的。
You could imagine doing this even faster.
你可以想象更快地做到这一点。
So that's actually not necessarily all the best for our security.
所以，这实际上并不一定是我们安全的最佳选择。
So what could we do instead of 10 digits?
那么，除了10位数字，我们还能做什么？
Well, most of you have probably upgraded a lot of your passwords
好吧，你们中的大多数人可能已经升级了你们的密码，
to maybe being alphabetical instead.
可能改为字母顺序。
So what if I instead were to ask the question-- and Carter, if you
那么，如果我改为问这个问题——卡特，如果你
want to rejoin me here in a second-- what if I instead were to consider
想在几秒钟后重新加入我——如果我改为考虑
maybe four-letter passcodes?
也许是四位字母密码？
So now we have A through Z four times.
所以现在我们有A到Z，重复四次。
And maybe we'll throw into the mix uppercase and--
也许我们会加入大写字母和——
well, let's just keep it four letters.
好吧，我们还是保留四个字母。
Let's just go ahead and do maybe uppercase and lowercase,
让我们继续，也许大写和小写，
so 52 possibilities.
所以有52种可能性。
This is going to give us 52 times 52 times 52 times 52.
这将给我们52乘以52乘以52乘以52。
And anyone want to ballpark the math here,
有人想在这里估计一下数学结果吗？
how many possible four-letter passcodes are there, roughly?
大约有多少个可能的四位字母密码？
7 million, yeah, so roughly 7 million, which is way bigger than 10,000.
700万，是的，所以大约700万，这比10,000大得多。
So, oh, I spoiled this, didn't I?
所以，哦，我把它说漏了，是不是？
Can you flip over?
你能翻过来吗？
So how many four-letter passcodes are there?
所以，有多少个四位字母密码？
It seems that most of you, 93% of you, in fact, got the answer right.
看来你们中的大多数人，事实上，有93%的人答对了。
Those of you who are changing your answer-- there
那些正在改变答案的人——
we go, no, definitely not that.
我们继续，不，绝对不是那样。
So, anyhow, I screwed up.
所以，无论如何，我搞砸了。
Order of operations matters in computing and, indeed, including lectures.
在计算中，运算顺序很重要，当然，包括讲座。
So 7 million, so the segue I wanted to make
所以，700万，所以我想做的是
is, OK, how long does that actually take to implement in code?
是，好吧，实际上用代码实现需要多长时间？
Well, let me just tweak our code here a little bit.
好吧，让我稍微调整一下我们的代码。
Let me go ahead and go back into the VS Code on my Mac in which I
让我继续，回到我的Mac上的VS Code，在那里我
had the same code as before.
拥有与之前相同的代码。
So let me shrink my terminal window, go back to the code from which I began.
所以让我缩小我的终端窗口，回到我开始使用的代码。
And let's just actually make a simple change.
让我们只做一个小小的改变。
Let me go ahead and simply change digits to something called ASCII letters.
让我继续，简单地将数字更改为名为ASCII字母的东西。
And this too is just a time saving technique.
这也是一种节省时间的方法。
So I don't have to type out A through Z and uppercase and lowercase like 52
所以我不必像52那样打出A到Z，以及大写和小写
total times.
总共次数。
And so I'm going to change digits to ASCII letters.
所以我要把数字改为ASCII字母。
And we'll get a quantitative sense of how long this takes.
我们将定量了解这需要多长时间。
So Python of crack.py, here's how long it takes
所以，Python的crack.py，这是完成700万次可能性所需的时间
to go through 7 million possibilities.
所需的时间。
All right, clearly slower because we haven't seen the end of the list yet.
好吧，很明显比较慢，因为我们还没有看到列表的结尾。
And you can see we're going through all of the lowercase letters here.
你可以看到我们正在遍历这里的所有小写字母。
We're about to hit Z. But now we're going through the uppercase letters.
我们即将到达Z。但现在我们正在遍历大写字母。
So it looks like the answer this time is going to be a few seconds, indeed.
所以看起来这次的答案是几秒钟，确实如此。
But definitely less than a minute would seem, at least
但至少看起来肯定不到一分钟
on this particular computer.
在这台特定的电脑上。
So odds are if I'm the adversary and I've
所以，如果我是对手，并且我
plugged this phone into someone's device-- maybe
将这部手机插到别人的设备上——也许
I'm not here in a lecture, but in Starbucks or an airport
我不是在这里上课，而是在星巴克或机场
or anywhere where I have physical opportunity to grab that device
或者任何我可以 physically 获得该设备的地方
and plug a cable in-- it's not going to take long to hack into that device
并插上电缆——破解那个设备不需要很长时间
either.
也是。
So what might be better than just digits and letters from the real world?
那么，除了现实世界中的数字和字母之外，还有什么更好的选择呢？
So add in some punctuation, which like almost every website
所以，添加一些标点符号，就像几乎所有网站
requires that we do.
要求我们做的那样。
Well, if we want to add punctuation into the mix, if I can get this segue
好吧，如果我们想添加标点符号，如果我能让这个衔接
correct so that we can now ask Carter one last time,
正确，这样我们现在可以最后一次问卡特，
how many four-character passcodes are possible where a character is
有多少个可能的四位字符密码，其中一个字符是
an uppercase or lowercase letter or a decimal digit or a punctuation symbol?
大写字母或小写字母或十进制数字或标点符号？
If you go to your device now, you'll see--
如果你现在去你的设备，你会看到——
if we want to flip over to the screen--
如果我们想翻到屏幕——
these possibilities.
这些可能性。
There's a million, maybe, a billion, a trillion, a quadrillion,
有一百万，也许，十亿，万亿，千万亿，
or a quintillion when it comes to a-- oh, wrong question.
或者百亿亿，当谈到一个——哦，问错了。
Wow, we're new here, OK.
哇，我们刚来这里，好吧。
OK, we're going to escalate things here.
好吧，我们要升级一下这里的事情。
How many eight-character passcodes are possible?
有多少个可能的八位字符密码？
We're going to make things more secure, even though I said four.
我们要让它更安全，即使我说的是四位。
We're now making it more secure to eight.
我们现在要把它设置为八位，以提高安全性。
All right, you want to flip over to the chart?
好的，你想翻到图表吗？
All right, so it looks like most of you are now
好吧，所以看起来你们中的大多数人现在
erring on the side of quintillion or quadrillion.
倾向于百亿亿或千万亿。
1% of you still said million, even though there's definitely more
你们中有 1% 的人仍然说百万，即使现在肯定比之前更多了
than there were a moment ago.
比之前更多。
But that's OK.
但这没关系。
So quadrillion-- quintillion is still winning.
所以四千万亿，五千万亿仍然领先。
And I think if we go and reveal this, with the math,
我认为如果我们用数学来揭示这一点，
you should be doing is 94 to the 4th power.
你应该做的是 94 的四次方。
Because there's 26 plus 26 plus 10 plus some more digits,
因为有 26 加 26 加 10 加一些更多的数字，
some punctuation digits in there as well.
还有标点符号。
So it's actually, oh, this is the other example, isn't it?
所以实际上，哦，这是另一个例子，不是吗？
This is embarrassing.
这太尴尬了。
All right, we had a good run in the past nine weeks instead.
好吧，我们过去九周表现还不错。
All right, so if you were curious as to how many four-character passwords are
好吧，如果你想知道有多少个四位字符的密码
possible, it's 78 million.
是可能的，那就是 7800 万。
But that's not the question at hand.
但这不是我们现在的问题。
The question at hand was, how many eight character passcodes are there?
问题是，有多少个八位字符的密码？
And in this case, the math you would be doing
在这种情况下，你应该做的数学运算
is 94 to the 8th power, which is a really big number.
是 94 的八次方，这是一个非常大的数字。
And, in fact, it's this number here, which
实际上，就是这里这个数字，它
is roughly 6 quadrillion possibilities.
大约有 6 万亿种可能性。
Now, I could go about actually doing this in code here.
现在，我可以在这里用代码来做这件事。
So let me actually, for a final flourish,
所以，为了最后一次点缀，
let me open up VS Code one last time here.
让我最后一次打开 VS Code。
And in VS Code, I'm going to go ahead and shrink my terminal window,
在 VS Code 中，我要缩小我的终端窗口，
go back into the code, and I'm going to import not just ASCII letters, not just
回到代码中，我不仅要导入 ASCII 字母，不仅要
digits, but punctuation as well, which is
导入数字，还要导入标点符号，它
going to give me like 32 punctuation symbols
将给我大约 32 个标点符号
from a typical US English keyboard.
来自一个典型的美国英语键盘。
And I'm going to go ahead and just concatenate them all together in one
然后我要把它们全部连接在一起，放到一个
big list by using the plus operator in Python
大列表中，使用 Python 中的加号运算符
to plus in both digits and punctuation.
将数字和标点符号加到一起。
And I'm going to change the 4 to an 8.
我将把 4 改成 8。
So this now, it's what four actual lines of code
所以现在，它有四行实际的代码
is, all it takes for an adversary to whip up some code,
就是，攻击者只需要编写一些代码，
find a cable as step two, and hack into a phone that
第二步找到一根电缆，就可以破解一台有
even has eight-character passcodes.
八位字符密码的手机。
Let me enlarge in my terminal window here, run
让我放大我的终端窗口，运行
for a final time Python of crack.py.
最后一次运行 Python crack.py。
And this I'll actually leave running for some time.
我会让它运行一段时间。
Because you can get already sort of a palpable feel of how much slower it
因为你已经可以感觉到它慢了很多，
is-- because these characters clearly haven't moved--
因为这些字符明显没有移动，
how long it's going to take.
它要花多久时间。
We might actually do-- need to do a bit more math.
我们可能需要做更多的数学运算。
Because doing just four-digit passcodes was super fast.
因为破解四位数字密码非常快。
Doing four-letter passcodes was slower, but still under a minute.
破解四位字母密码速度较慢，但也不到一分钟。
We'll see maybe in time how long this actually runs for.
我们来看看它到底要运行多久。
But this clearly seems to be better, at least for some definition of better.
但对于某种意义上的“更好”来说，这似乎明显更好了。
But it should hopefully not be that easy to hack into a system.
但希望破解系统不会那么容易。
What does your own device probably do to defend against that brute force attack?
你的设备可能做了什么来防御这种暴力攻击？
Yeah.
是的。
AUDIENCE: Gives you a limited number of tries.
观众：限制你尝试的次数。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so it gives you a limited number of tries.
大卫·马兰：是的，它限制你尝试的次数。
So odds are, at least once in your life, you've somehow locked yourself out
所以，你至少曾经有一次把自己锁在
of a device, typically after typing your passcode more than 10 times
设备外面，通常是你在输入密码超过 10 次
or 10 attempts or maybe it's your siblings or your roommate's phone
或 10 次尝试之后，或者可能是你兄弟姐妹或室友的手机
that you realize this is a feature of iPhones and Android devices as well.
你才意识到，这也是 iPhone 和 Android 设备的一个功能。
But here's a screenshot of what an iPhone might
但这里是一个 iPhone 可能
do if you do try to input the wrong passcode maybe 10 or so times.
会做的事情，如果你尝试输入错误的密码 10 次左右。
Notice that it's really telling you to try again in one minute.
请注意，它会让你在一分钟后重新尝试。
So this isn't fundamentally changing what the adversary can do.
所以这并没有从根本上改变攻击者可以做的事情。
The adversary can absolutely use those same four lines of code with a cable
攻击者完全可以使用相同的四行代码和一根电缆
and try to hack into your device.
尝试破解你的设备。
But what has this just done?
但这做了什么？
It's significantly increased the cost to the adversary,
它大大增加了攻击者的成本，
where the cost might be measured in sheer number amount of time--
成本可以用时间来衡量，比如分钟、秒、小时、天或更长时间。
like minutes, seconds, hours, days, or beyond.
分钟、秒、小时、天或更长时间。
Maybe it's increased the cost in the sense of risk.
也许它从风险的角度提高了成本。
Why?
为什么？
Because if this were like a movie incarnation of this
因为如果这像电影中的情节一样
and the adversary has just plugged into the phone
攻击者刚刚连接到手机
and is kind of creepily looking around until you come back,
并且在你看不到的时候偷偷地四处张望，直到你回来，
it's going to take way too long for them to safely get away with that,
他们要安全地逃脱，需要花费太长时间，
assuming your passcode is not 123456, it's
假设你的密码不是 123456，而是
somewhere in the middle of that massive search space.
处于那个巨大的搜索空间的中间位置。
So this just kind of fundamentally raises the bar to the adversary.
所以，这从根本上提高了攻击者的门槛。
And that's one of the biggest takeaways of cybersecurity in general.
这正是网络安全的一大启示。
It's completely naive to think in terms of absolute security
认为绝对的安全，完全是天真幼稚的。
or to even say a sentence like "my website is secure" or even
或者说“我的网站很安全”这样的话，甚至
"my home is physically secure."
“我的家很安全”。
Why?
为什么？
Well, for a couple of reasons, like, one, an adversary
有很多原因，比如，首先，一个攻击者
with enough time, energy, motivation, or resources
只要有足够的时间、精力、动力或资源
can surely get into most any system and can surely get into most any home.
肯定可以破解大多数系统，肯定可以进入大多数房屋。
But the other thing to consider, unfortunately,
但不幸的是，还有另外一点需要考虑，
that if we're the good people in this story and the adversaries
如果我们是在这个故事中扮演好人，而攻击者
are the bad people, you and I rather have to be perfect.
是坏人，你我必须完美无缺。
In the physical world, we have to lock every door, every window.
在现实世界中，我们必须锁上每一扇门，每一扇窗户。
Because if we mess up just one spot, the adversary can get in.
因为只要我们犯一个错误，攻击者就可以进来。
And so where there's sort of this imbalance.
因此，这种不平衡存在于
The adversary just has to find the window that's
攻击者只需要找到窗户
ajar to get into your physical home.
开着，就可以进入你的家。
The adversary just needs to find one user who's
攻击者只需要找到一个
got a really bad password to somehow get into that system.
密码很糟糕的用户，就可以进入那个系统。
And so cybersecurity is hard.
网络安全很难。
And so what we'll see today really are techniques
所以我们今天将看到的是一些技巧
that can let you create a gauntlet of defenses-- so not just one,
可以让你构建一道防线，不仅仅是一道
but maybe two, maybe three.
而是可能两道，甚至三道。
And even if the adversary gets in, another tenant of cybersecurity
即使对手闯入了，网络安全另一个原则
is at least, let's have mechanisms in place that detect
至少是，让我们拥有能够检测到的机制
the adversary, some kind of monitoring, automatic emails.
对手，某种监控，自动邮件。
You can increasingly see this already in the real world.
你可以在现实世界中越来越频繁地看到这一点。
If you log into your Instagram account from a different city or state
如果你从不同的城市或州登录你的 Instagram 账户
suddenly because maybe you're traveling, you
突然间，可能是因为你正在旅行，你会
will-- if you've opted into settings like these-- often
如果启用了这些设置，你经常会
get a notification or an email saying, hey,
收到通知或电子邮件，说，嘿，
you seems to have logged in from Palo Alto rather than Cambridge.
你好像是从帕洛阿尔托而不是剑桥登录的。
Is this, in fact, you?
这确实是你的操作吗？
So even though we might not be able to keep the adversary out,
所以，即使我们可能无法阻止对手进入，
let's at least minimize the window of opportunity or damage
让我们至少将可乘之机或造成的损害降到最低
by letting humans like us know that something's been compromised.
通过让我们这些人类知道某些东西已经被泄露。
Of course, there is a downside here.
当然，这里也存在弊端。
And this is another theme of cybersecurity.
这也是网络安全另一个主题。
Every time you improve something, you've got to pay a price.
每次你改进某些东西，你都得付出代价。
There's going to be a tradeoff.
会有权衡取舍。
And we've seen this with time and space and money and other such resources
我们在设计系统的时候，已经见识过时间、空间、金钱和这类资源方面的权衡取舍。
when it comes to designing systems already.
时间、空间、金钱和这类资源方面的权衡取舍。
What's the downside of this mechanism?
这种机制的弊端是什么？
Why is this perhaps a bad thing or what's the downside to you,
为什么这可能是一件坏事，或者对你来说，弊端是什么，
the good person in the story?
故事中的好人？
Yeah.
是的。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, if you've just forgotten your passcode,
大卫·马兰：是的，如果你忘记了密码，
it's going to be more difficult for you to log in.
你登录就会更困难。
Or maybe you just really need to get into your phone now
或者你可能现在真的需要进入你的手机
and you don't really want to wait a minute.
你不想等一分钟。
And if you, worse, if you keep trying, sometimes it'll
更糟糕的是，如果你一直尝试，有时会
change to two minutes, five minutes, one hour.
变成两分钟、五分钟、一个小时。
It'll increase exponentially.
它会呈指数级增长。
Why?
为什么？
Because Apple and Google figure that, they don't necessarily
因为苹果和谷歌认为，他们不一定
know what the right cutoff is.
知道正确的截止时间。
Maybe it's 10, maybe it's fewer, maybe it's more.
可能是 10 次，也可能更少，也可能更多。
But at some point, it is much more likely
但在某些时候，这更有可能是
that this is a hacker trying to get in than it is for getting your passcode.
黑客试图入侵，而不是你忘记密码。
But in the corporate world, it can be even worse.
但在企业界，情况可能更糟。
There's a feature that lets phones essentially self-destruct whereby
有一个功能可以让手机自动销毁，这样
rather than just waiting you wait a minute,
而不是仅仅让你等待一分钟，
it will wipe the device, more dramatically.
它会更剧烈地擦除设备。
The presumption being that, no, no, no, no, no, if this is a corporate phone,
假设是，不，不，不，不，不，如果这是一部公司手机，
let's lock it down further so that it is an adversary,
让我们进一步锁定它，这样如果是一个对手，
the data is gone after 10 failed attempts.
数据会在 10 次尝试失败后消失。
But there's other mechanisms as well.
但也存在其他机制。
In addition to logging into phones via passcodes,
除了通过密码登录手机，
there's also websites like Gmail, for instance.
还有像 Gmail 这样的网站。
And it's very common, therefore, to log in to websites like these.
因此，登录这些网站非常普遍。
And odds are, statistically, a lot of you
从统计学上讲，你们很多人
are in the habit of reusing passwords.
有重复使用密码的习惯。
Like, no, don't nod if you are.
比如，不，如果你有，不要点头。
We have cameras everywhere.
到处都是摄像头。
But maybe you're in the habit of reusing it.
但你可能习惯了重复使用它。
Why?
为什么？
Because it's hard to remember really big long cryptic passwords.
因为很难记住真正很长很复杂的密码。
So mathematically, there's surely an advantage there.
所以从数学角度来说，这确实有优势。
Why?
为什么？
Because it just makes it so much harder, more time-consuming,
因为这使得对手入侵变得更加困难，更加耗时，
more risky for an adversary to get in.
风险更大。
But the other tradeoff is like, my God, I just can't even
但另一个权衡是，我的天，我真的记不住
remember most of my passwords as a result
大部分密码了
unless I reuse the one good password I thought of and memorized already
除非我重复使用我想到并记住的那个好密码
or maybe I write it down on a post-it note on my monitor,
或者我可能把它写在显示器上的便签纸上，
as all too often happens in corporate workplaces.
在企业工作场所，这种情况太常见了。
Or maybe you're being clever and in your top right drawer,
或者你可能很聪明，在你最上面的右边的抽屉里，
you've got a printout of all of your accounts.
你放着你所有账户的打印副本。
Well, if you do, like ha-ha, so do a lot of other people.
好吧，如果你这样做了，哈哈，很多人也这样做。
Or maybe it's a little more secure than that,
或者可能比这更安全一点，
but there are sociological side effects of these technological policies that
但这些科技政策带来了社会影响，
really until recent years were maybe underappreciated.
直到最近几年才被人们认识到。
The academics, the IT administrators were mandating policies
学者们、IT 管理员们都强制要求这些政策
that you and I as human users were not necessarily behaving properly
而你我作为用户，并不一定会按照这些政策行事
in the face of.
面对这些政策。
So nowadays, there are things called password managers.
所以现在有叫做密码管理器的工具。
And a password manager is just a piece of software on Macs,
密码管理器仅仅是 Mac 上的一段软件，
on PCs, on phones that manage your passwords for you.
PC 上，手机上的一段软件，它可以为你管理密码。
What this means specifically is when you go
具体来说，这意味着当你
to a website for the very first time, you, the human,
第一次访问一个网站的时候，你，作为一个人类，
don't need to choose your password anymore.
不再需要选择你的密码了。
You instead click a button or use some keyboard shortcut.
你只需要点击一个按钮或者使用键盘快捷键。
And the software generates a really long cryptic password for you
软件会为你生成一个非常长且复杂的密码
that's not even eight characters.
甚至都不需要 8 个字符。
It might be 16 or 32 characters, can be even bigger than that, but with lots
可能是 16 个字符或 32 个字符，甚至更多，但它拥有大量的
of randomness.
随机性。
Definitely not going to be on that top 10 or that top 100 list.
肯定不会出现在前 10 名或前 100 名的列表中。
The software thereafter remembers that password
软件之后会记住这个密码
for you and even your username, whether it's your email address or something
还有你的用户名，无论它是你的电子邮件地址还是其他东西。
else.
其他东西。
And it saves it onto your Mac or your phone or your PC's disk or hard drive.
它会将密码保存到你的 Mac、手机、PC 的磁盘或硬盘上。
The next time you visit that same website, what you can do
下次你访问同一个网站时，你可以
is via menu or, better yet, a keyboard shortcut, log into the website
通过菜单，或者更好的是，键盘快捷键登录网站。
without even remembering or even knowing your password.
甚至不记得也不认识你的密码。
I mean, to this day, I'll tell you, I don't even
我的意思是，直到今天，我告诉你，我甚至
know anymore 99% of my own passwords.
不再知道我自己的 99% 的密码。
Rather, I rely on software like this to do the heavy lifting for me.
相反，我依靠像这样的软件来为我完成繁重的工作。
But there's an obvious downside here, which
但是这里有一个明显的缺点，那就是
might be what if you're doing this?
也许你正在做这件事？
Yeah.
是的。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Right, so what if they find out the one password
大卫·马兰：没错，那么如果他们发现保护这个软件的那个密码呢？
that's protecting this software?
那个保护这个软件的密码？
Because unstated by me up until now is that this password manager itself
因为我之前没有说明的是，这个密码管理器本身
has a primary password that protects all of those other eggs in the one basket,
有一个主密码，保护着所有那些其他在一个篮子里的鸡蛋，
so to speak.
可以这么说。
And my one primary password for my own password manager,
而我自己的密码管理器的唯一主密码，
it is really long and hard to guess.
它真的很长，很难猜到。
And the odds that anyone's going to guess
而且任何人都能猜到的可能性
are just so low that I'm comfortable with that
实在是太低了，以至于我对此感到很舒服
being the one really difficult thing that I've committed to my memory.
成为我唯一要记住的难题。
But the problem is if someone does figure it out nonetheless somehow
但问题是，如果有人不知何故真的猜出来了
or, worse, I forget what it is.
或者更糟的是，我忘记了它是什么。
Now, I've not lost access to one account, but all of my accounts.
现在，我失去了对一个账户的访问权限，而是所有账户的访问权限。
Now, that might be too high of a price to pay.
现在，这可能是一个过高的代价。
But, again, if you're in the habit of choosing easy passwords like being
但是，再说一次，如果你习惯于选择像这样的简单密码
on that top 10 list, reusing passwords, it's probably a net
出现在前十名的名单上，重复使用密码，这可能是一个
positive to incur this single risk versus the many risks you're
积极的做法，承担这个单一的风险，而不是你承担的许多风险
incurring across the board with all of these other sites.
你在所有其他网站上都承担着这些风险。
As for what you can use, increasingly our operating systems
至于你可以使用什么，我们的操作系统越来越多地
come with support for this, be it in the Apple world, Google, Microsoft world,
开始支持这一点，无论是苹果世界、谷歌、微软世界，
or the like.
或者类似的东西。
There's third party software you can pay for and download.
有一些你可以付费下载的第三方软件。
But even then, I would beware.
但即使那样，我也会小心。
And I would ask friends whose opinion you trust or do
我建议询问你信任的朋友，或者
some googling for reviews and the like.
在谷歌上搜索一些评论等等。
All too often in the software world have password managers
在软件世界里，密码管理器经常
been determined to be buggy themselves.
被发现自身存在漏洞。
I mean, you've seen in weeks of CS50 how easy it is to introduce bugs.
我的意思是，你在 CS50 的几周里已经看到了引入漏洞是多么容易。
And even the best of programmers still introduce bugs to software.
即使是最好的程序员也会在软件中引入漏洞。
So you're also trusting that the companies making this password
所以你也在信任那些制作这个密码的公司
management software is really good at it.
管理软件真的做得很好。
And that's not always the case.
但情况并不总是这样。
So beware there too.
所以也要注意这一点。
But we'll also focus today on some of the fundamentals
但我们今天也会关注这些公司可以用来更好地保护你的数据的几个基本原理。
that these companies can be using to better protect your data as well.
这些公司可以用来更好地保护你的数据。
But there's another mechanism, which odds are you're in the habit of using.
但是还有另一种机制，你很可能习惯于使用它。
Two-factor authentication, like most of us
双因素身份验证，就像我们大多数人一样
probably have to use this for some of your accounts--
可能需要在一些账户中使用它——
your Harvard account, your Yale account, maybe your bank accounts, or the like.
你的哈佛账户、你的耶鲁账户，也许还有你的银行账户等等。
So what is two-factor authentication in a nutshell?
那么，双因素身份验证简而言之是什么呢？
Yeah.
是的。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, you get a second factor
大卫·马兰：没错，你获得了一个第二个因素
that you have to provide to the website or application
你需要提供给网站或应用程序，
to prove that it's you like a text to your phone
来证明是你，比如发送短信到你的手机
or maybe it's an actual application that gets push notifications or the like.
或者它可能是一个应用程序，它会发送推送通知等等。
Maybe in the corporate world, it's actually
在公司里，它实际上是
a tiny little device with a screen on it that's on your keychain or the like.
一个带屏幕的小装置，放在你的钥匙链上等等。
Maybe it's actually a USB dongle that you have to plug into your work laptop.
它可能实际上是一个 USB 钥匙，你必须将其插入你的工作笔记本电脑。
In short, it's some second factor.
简而言之，它是第二个因素。
And by factor, I mean something technical.
而因素的意思是技术上的东西。
It's not just a second password, which would be one factor.
它不仅仅是第二个密码，那只是一个因素。
It's a second fundamentally different factor.
它是第二个从根本上不同的因素。
So generally speaking in the world of two-factor authentication or 2FA or MFA
所以，一般来说，在双因素身份验证或 2FA 或 MFA 的世界里
is the generalization as multi-factor authentication,
更一般地说，是多因素身份验证，
you have not just a password, which is something you know,
你不止有一个密码，那是你知道的东西，
the second factor is usually something you have--
第二个因素通常是你拥有的东西——
whether it's your phone or that application or the keychain.
无论是你的手机、那个应用程序还是钥匙链。
It might also be biometrics like your fingerprints, your retinas,
它也可能是生物识别技术，比如你的指纹、你的视网膜，
or something else physically about you.
或者其他关于你身体的东西。
But it's something that significantly decreases the probability
但它能够显著降低某个攻击者进入那个账户的可能性。
that some adversary is going to get into that account.
某个攻击者进入那个账户的可能性。
Why?
为什么？
Because right now, if you've only got a username and password,
因为现在，如果你只有用户名和密码，
your adversaries are literally every human in the world
你的攻击者实际上是世界上所有的人
with an internet connection, arguably.
拥有互联网连接的人，可以说是这样。
But as soon as you introduce 2FA, now it's
但一旦你引入了 2FA，现在就只有
only people on campus or, more narrowly, only the people in Starbucks
校园里的人，或者更确切地说，只有在星巴克的人
at that moment who might physically have access
那一刻可能对你和你的第二个因素有物理访问权限的人。
to your person and your second factor, in this case.
在这种情况下，对你和你第二个因素有物理访问权限的人。
More technically, what those technologies do is they send you
更技术地说，这些技术做的是它们会向你发送
a one-time passcode, which is further secure because once it's used,
一个一次性密码，它更加安全，因为一旦使用，
there's hopefully some database that remembers that it has been used
希望有一些数据库会记住它已经被使用过
and cannot be used again.
并且不能再次使用。
So an adversary can't like sniff the airwaves and replay
所以，攻击者不能像嗅探无线电波那样，在下次它们确实到期时重复使用
that passcode the next time they, indeed, expire,
那个密码。
which adds some additional defense.
这增加了一些额外的防御。
And you might type it into a phone or maybe a web app that
你可能会将它输入手机，或者可能输入一个看起来像这样的网页应用。
looks a little something like this.
看起来像这样。
So passwords thus far, some defenses, therefore, any questions on this
所以，到目前为止的密码，一些防御，因此，关于这个机制，有什么问题吗？
here mechanism?
机制？
No?
没有？
All right, well, let's consider this.
好吧，让我们考虑一下。
Odds are, with some frequency, you forget these passwords, especially
很可能，你会经常忘记这些密码，尤其是在
if you're not using a password manager.
你不使用密码管理器的情况下。
And so you go to Gmail and you actually have
所以你进入 Gmail，你实际上拥有
to click a link like this, Forgot Password.
点击像这样的链接，忘记密码。
And then it typically emails you to initiate
然后它通常会向你发送电子邮件，以启动
a process of resetting that password.
重置密码的过程。
But if you can recall, has anyone ever clicked a link like that
但是如果你能回忆起来，有人点击过这样的链接吗？
and then got an email with your password in the email?
然后收到了包含你的密码的电子邮件？
Maybe if you ever see this in the wild, that
也许如果你在现实生活中看到这种情况，那么
is to say in the real world, that is horrible, horrible design.
也就是说在现实世界中，这是一种糟糕的设计，非常糟糕。
Why?
为什么？
Because well-designed websites, not unlike CS50 Finance,
因为设计良好的网站，就像 CS50 Finance 一样，
which had a users table, should not be storing username-- rather,
它有一个用户表，不应该存储用户名——更确切地说，
should not be storing passwords in the clear, as it actually is.
不应该以明文形式存储密码，而实际上它就是这么做的。
It should somehow be obfuscated so that even
它应该以某种方式被混淆，即使
if your database from CS50 Finance or Google's database
你的 CS50 Finance 数据库或谷歌的数据库
is hacked and compromised and sold on the web,
被黑客入侵并被盗，并在网上出售，
it should not be as simple as doing like select star
它不应该像使用 select star 一样简单
from Account semicolon to see what your actual passwords are.
从 Account 表中查询，以查看你的实际密码。
And the mechanism that well-designed websites use
而设计良好的网站所使用的机制
is actually a primitive back from like week 5 when we
实际上是一种原始的技术，可以追溯到第 5 周，当时我们
talked about hashing and hash tables.
讨论了哈希和哈希表。
This time, we're using it for slightly different purposes.
这一次，我们将它用于略微不同的目的。
So in the world of passwords, on the server side, there's often a database
所以，在密码的世界中，在服务器端，通常有一个数据库
or maybe, more simply, a text file somewhere on the server
或者，更简单地说，在服务器上的某个地方有一个文本文件
that just associates usernames with passwords.
它只是将用户名与密码关联起来。
So to keep things simple, if there's at least two users like Alice and Bob,
为了简单起见，如果至少有两个用户，比如 Alice 和 Bob，
Alice's password is maybe apple.
Alice 的密码可能是 apple。
Bob's password is maybe banana, just to keep the mnemonics kind of simple.
Bob 的密码可能是 banana，只是为了让助记符尽可能简单。
If though that were the case on the server
如果服务器上的情况确实如此
and that server is compromised, whoever the hacker now
而且服务器被入侵了，现在无论是谁入侵了服务器
has access to every username and every password, which in and of itself
都可以访问每个用户名和每个密码，这本身
might not be a huge deal because maybe the server administrators can just
可能不是什么大问题，因为服务器管理员可以
disable all of the accounts, make everyone change their password,
禁用所有帐户，让每个人更改他们的密码，
and move on.
然后继续。
But there's also this attack known as password stuffing, which
但也有一种被称为密码填充的攻击，它
is a weirdly technical term, which means when you compromise one database,
是一个奇怪的技术术语，意思是当你入侵了一个数据库，
you know what?
你知道吗？
Take advantage of the naivety of a lot of us users.
利用我们很多用户的天真。
Try the compromised Apple password, the banana
尝试被盗的 Apple 密码，香蕉
password not on the compromised website, but other websites
密码不在被盗的网站上，而是在其他网站上
that you and I might have access to, the presumption
你我可能可以访问的网站，假设
being that some of us in this room are using
是，我们房间里的一些人正在使用
the same passwords in multiple places.
同一个密码在多个地方。
So it's bad if your password is compromised on one server
所以，如果你的密码在一个服务器上被盗了
because, by transitivity, so can all of your other accounts be compromised.
那么，通过传递性，你所有的其他帐户也可能被入侵。
So in the world of hashing, this was the picture
所以，在哈希的世界中，这就是我们之前画的图
we drew some time ago, we can apply this same logic whereby, mathematically,
我们之前画的图，我们可以应用同样的逻辑，从数学上来说，
a hash function is like some function F and the input is X
一个哈希函数就像某个函数 F，输入是 X
and the output or the range is F of X. That
输出或范围是 F(X)。那
was sort of the fancy way of describing mathematically
是一种用数学方法描述哈希过程的奇特方式
hashing as a process weeks ago.
作为几周前的过程。
But here, at a simpler level, the input to this process
但是在这里，在一个更简单的层面上，这个过程的输入
is going to be your actual password.
将是你的实际密码。
The output is going to be a hash value, which in week 5
输出将是一个哈希值，在第 5 周
was something simple generally like a number--
通常是一个简单的东西，比如一个数字——
1 or 2 or 3 based on the first letter.
1 或 2 或 3，取决于第一个字母。
That's not going to be quite as naive an approach as we
那不会像我们所采用的那样天真。
take in the password world.
在密码世界中。
It's going to look a little more cryptic.
它看起来会更神秘。
So Apple weeks ago might have just been 1, banana might have been 3.
所以几周前的 Apple 可能是 1，banana 可能是 3。
But now let me propose that in the world of real world system design, what
但是现在让我提出，在现实世界系统设计的领域中，
the database people should actually store
数据库人员实际上应该存储的
is not apple, but rather this cryptic value.
不是 apple，而是这个神秘的值。
And you can think of this as sort of random, but it's not random.
你可以把它想象成某种随机的东西，但它不是随机的。
Because it is the result of an algorithm, some mathematical function
因为它是一个算法的结果，某个数学函数
that someone implemented and smart people evaluated and said,
有人实现了它，聪明人评估了它，并说，
yes, this seems to be secure, secure in the sense
是的，这似乎是安全的，安全的意义在于
that this hash function is meant to be one way.
这个哈希函数是单向的。
So this is not encryption, a la Caesar Cipher from weeks
所以这不是加密，比如几周前的凯撒密码
ago whereby you could just add 1 to encrypt and subtract 1 to decrypt.
之前，你只需加 1 来加密，减 1 来解密。
This is one way in the sense that given this value,
这是单向的，因为给定这个值，
it should be pretty much impossible mathematically to reverse the process
从数学上来说，逆转这个过程几乎是不可能的
and figure out that the user's password was originally apple.
并找出用户的密码最初是 apple。
Meanwhile banana, back in week 5 for simplicity, for hashing into a table,
同时，banana，回到第 5 周，为了简单起见，为了将其哈希到一个表中，
we might have had a simple output of 2, since B
我们可能得到一个简单的输出 2，因为 B
is the second letter of the English alphabet.
是英语字母表中的第二个字母。
But now the hash value of banana, thanks to a fancier mathematical function,
但现在，banana 的哈希值，由于更复杂的数学函数，
is actually going to be something more cryptic like this.
实际上将是一个更神秘的东西，像这样。
And so what the server really does is store not apple and banana, but rather
所以服务器实际上存储的不是 apple 和 banana，而是
those two seemingly cryptic values.
这两个看起来很神秘的值。
And then when the human, be it Alice or Bob,
然后，当人类，无论是 Alice 还是 Bob，
logs in to a web form with their actual username and password, like Alice,
登录到一个带有其真实用户名和密码的网页表单，比如 Alice，
apple, Bob, banana, the website no longer even
apple，Bob，banana，网站不再
knows that Alice's password is apple and that Bob's is banana.
知道 Alice 的密码是 apple，Bob 的密码是 banana。
But that's OK.
但没关系。
Because so long as the server uses the same code
因为只要服务器使用与
as it was using when these folks registered for accounts,
这些人注册帐户时所使用的代码相同，
Alice can type in apple, hit Enter, send it via HTTP to the server.
Alice 可以输入 apple，按回车键，通过 HTTP 发送到服务器。
The server can run that same hash function on A-P-P-L-E.
服务器可以对 A-P-P-L-E 运行相同的哈希函数。
And if the value matches, it can conclude with high probability, yes,
如果值匹配，它可以以很高的概率得出结论，是的，
this is in fact, the original Alice or this, in fact, is the original Bob.
这实际上是最初的 Alice，或者实际上是最初的 Bob。
So the server never saves the password, but it does use the same hash function
所以服务器从不保存密码，但它确实使用了相同的哈希函数
to compare those same hash values again and again whenever these folks log in
每次这些用户登录时，都要不断比较相同的哈希值
again and again.
一次又一次
So, in reality, here's a simple one-way hash for both Alice's
所以，实际上，这里有一个简单的一路哈希值，用于 Alice 的
and Bob's passwords in the real world.
以及 Bob 在现实世界中的密码
It's even longer, this is to say, than what I
它更长，也就是说，比我
used as shorter examples a moment ago.
刚才用作较短示例的还要长
But there is a corner case here.
但是这里有一个特殊情况
Suppose that an adversary is smart and has some free time
假设攻击者很聪明，而且有一些空闲时间
and isn't necessarily interested in getting into someone's account
并且不一定要立即进入别人的账户
right now, but wants to do a bit of prework
而是想做一些预备工作
to decrease the future cost of getting into someone's account.
以便降低未来进入别人账户的成本
There is a technical term known as a rainbow table,
有一个技术术语叫做彩虹表
which is essentially like a dictionary in the Python sense or the SQL sense,
本质上就像 Python 或 SQL 中的字典
whereby in advance an adversary could just try hashing all of the fruits
因此，攻击者可以提前尝试对所有水果进行哈希运算
of the world or, really, all of the English words of the world or, rather,
全世界或所有英文单词，或者说
all possible four-digit, four-character, eight-character passcodes in advance
提前所有可能的四位数、四字符和八字符密码
and just store them in two columns--
并将其存储在两列中
the password, like 0000 or apple or banana,
密码，比如 0000、apple 或 banana
and then just store in advance the hash values.
然后提前存储哈希值
So the adversary could effectively reverse engineer the hash
所以攻击者可以有效地逆向破解哈希值
by just looking at a hash, comparing it against its massive database of hashes,
只需查看哈希值，将其与庞大的哈希值数据库进行比较
and figuring out what password originally correspond to that.
并找出最初与之对应的密码
Why then is this still relatively safe?
为什么这仍然相对安全？
Rainbow tables are concerning.
彩虹表令人担忧
But they don't defeat passwords altogether.
但它们不会完全破解密码
Why might that be?
为什么呢？
Yeah.
是的
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: OK, so the adversary might not
DAVID MALAN：好的，所以攻击者可能不会
know exactly what hash function the company is using.
知道公司使用的哈希函数的具体内容
Generally speaking, you would not want to necessarily keep that private.
一般来说，你不会想要将其保密
That would be considered security through obscurity.
这将被视为通过模糊性来实现安全性
And all it takes is like one bad actor to tell the adversary what
而且只需要一个坏人告诉攻击者
hash function is being used.
使用的哈希函数是什么
And then that would put your security more at risk.
然后你的安全就会面临更大的风险
So generally in the security world, openness
所以，在安全界，开放性
when it comes to the algorithms in process
对于算法而言
is generally considered best practice.
通常被认为是最佳实践
And the reality is, there's a few popular hash functions out there
现实是，有一些流行的哈希函数
that any company should be using.
任何公司都应该使用
And so it's not really keeping a secret anyway.
所以，无论如何，它并不是真正保密
But other thoughts?
还有其他想法吗？
Why is this rainbow table not such a concern?
为什么彩虹表不是那么令人担忧？
AUDIENCE: It takes a lot longer for the [INAUDIBLE]..
观众：这需要花费攻击者更长的时间 [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: It takes a lot longer for the adversary
DAVID MALAN：这需要花费攻击者更长的时间
to access that information because this table could get long.
来访问这些信息，因为这个表可能会变得很长
And even more along those lines-- anyone want to push a little harder?
还有，还有没有其他想法？
This doesn't necessarily put all of our passwords at risk.
这并不一定会让所有密码面临风险
It easily puts our four-digit passcodes at risk.
这很容易让我们的四位数密码面临风险
Why?
为什么？
Because this table, this dictionary would have, what, 10,000 rows?
因为这个表，这个字典会包含多少行？10,000 行？
And we've seen that you can search that kind of like that
我们已经看到，你可以像这样搜索它
or even regenerate all of the possible values.
甚至重新生成所有可能的值
But once you get to eight-character passcodes,
但一旦你使用八字符密码
I said it was 4 quadrillion possibilities.
我说过，它有 4 千万亿种可能性
That's a crazy big dictionary in Python or crazy big list
这在 Python 中是一个非常大的字典或列表
of some sort in Python.
在 Python 中
That's just way more RAM or memory than a typical adversary is going to have.
这比一般攻击者拥有的 RAM 或内存要多得多
Now, maybe if it's a particularly resourced adversary like a government,
现在，如果是一个拥有大量资源的攻击者，比如政府
a state more generally, maybe they do have supercomputers
更一般地说，国家，也许他们确实拥有超级计算机
that can fit that much information.
可以容纳那么多的信息
But, fine, then use a 16-character passcode
但是，好吧，那么使用一个 16 字符密码
and make it an unpronounceable long search space
并将其设置为一个不可读的较长的搜索空间
that's way bigger than 4 quadrillion.
比 4 千万亿还要大得多
So it's a threat, but only if you're on that horrible top 10 list or top 100
所以它是一种威胁，但只有当你使用那些糟糕的排名前 10 位或排名前 100 位
or short passcode list that we've discussed thus far.
或较短的密码列表，这些我们之前已经讨论过了
So here's though a related threat that's just worth knowing about.
所以这里有一个相关的威胁，值得了解
What's problematic here?
这里有什么问题？
If we introduce two more users, Carol and Charlie,
如果我们再引入两个用户，Carol 和 Charlie
and just for the semantics of it, whose password happened to be cherry.
为了语义，他们的密码恰好是 cherry
What if they both happened to have the same password and this database
如果他们两个恰好拥有相同的密码，而且这个数据库
is compromised?
被攻破了？
Some hacker gets in.
一些黑客入侵了
And just to be clear, we wouldn't be storing apple, banana, cherry, cherry.
明确地说，我们不会存储 apple、banana、cherry、cherry
We'd still be storing, according to this story, these hashes.
我们仍然会存储，根据这个故事，这些哈希值
But why is this still concerning?
但为什么这仍然令人担忧？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
DAVID MALAN：没错
If you figure out just one of them, now you've got the other.
如果你破解了一个，那么你就得到了另一个
And this is, in some sense, just leaking information, right?
从某种意义上说，这只是信息泄露，对吧？
I don't maybe at a glance what I could do with this information.
我可能无法一眼看出我能用这些信息做什么
But if Carol and Charlie have the same password, you know what?
但如果 Carol 和 Charlie 拥有相同的密码，你知道吗？
I bet they have the same password on other systems as well.
我敢打赌，他们可能在其他系统中也拥有相同的密码
You're leaking information that just does no good for anyone.
你泄露了对任何人都没有好处的信息
So how can we avoid that?
那么如何避免这种情况呢？
Well, we probably don't want to force Carol or Charlie to change
好吧，我们可能不想强迫 Carol 或 Charlie 更改
their password, especially when they're registering.
他们的密码，尤其是在他们注册的时候
You definitely don't want to say, sorry, someone's already using that password,
你绝对不想说，对不起，有人已经在使用那个密码了
you can't use it as well.
你也不能使用
Because that too would leak information.
因为那样也会泄露信息
But there's this technique in computing known as salting
但是，在计算中有一种叫做加盐的技术
whereby we can do this instead.
我们可以用它来代替
If cherry we in this scheme hashes to a value like this, you know what?
如果 cherry 在这个方案中被哈希成这样的值，你知道吗？
Let's go ahead and sprinkle a little bit of salt into the process.
让我们在过程中撒点盐。
And it's sort of a metaphorical salt whereby this hash function now takes
这是一种比喻性的盐，这个哈希函数现在需要
two inputs, not just the password, but some other value known as a salt.
两个输入，不仅仅是密码，还有另一个称为盐的值。
And the salt can be generally something super short like two characters even,
盐通常可以是超短的，甚至只有两个字符，
or something longer.
或更长。
And the idea is that this salt, much like a recipe,
这个盐的想法，就像一个食谱一样，
should of perturb the output a little bit,
应该会稍微扰乱输出，
make it taste a little bit differently, if you will.
如果你愿意，让它尝起来有点不同。
And so concretely, if we take the word cherry and then when Carol registers,
因此具体地说，如果我们取单词 "cherry"，然后当 Carol 注册时，
for instance, we randomly choose a salt of 50, 5-0, so two characters,
例如，我们随机选择一个盐 50，5-0，也就是两个字符，
the hash value now-- because there's two inputs--
哈希值现在，因为有两个输入，
might now be this value.
现在可能是这个值。
But if for Charlie, we still have cherry, but we change the 50,
但是如果对于 Charlie 来说，我们仍然有 "cherry"，但是我们改变了 50，
we might see this instead.
我们可能会看到这个。
Notice that for this first example, Carol, 50,
注意，对于第一个例子，Carol，50，
the salt is preserved in the hash value, just so you know what it was
盐被保留在哈希值中，这样你就能知道它是什么
and you can sprinkle the same amount of salt, so to speak, next time.
下次你可以撒同样量的盐，这么说吧。
But that's the whole hash value for Carol in this case.
但那是这个例子中 Carol 的整个哈希值。
But if Charlie also has a password of cherry, but we change the salt to,
但是如果 Charlie 也有一个密码是 "cherry"，但是我们把盐改成，
say, 49 arbitrarily, that whole hash value changed.
比如，任意地改为 49，整个哈希值就改变了。
And so now in my hash database, I'm going to see different salts there,
所以现在在我的哈希数据库中，我会看到不同的盐，
different values, which is going to effectively cover up the fact
不同的值，这将有效地掩盖这样一个事实，
that Carol and Charlie have the same password.
Carol 和 Charlie 有相同的密码。
Now, if we have so many users that we run out of salts,
现在，如果我们有太多用户以至于我们用完盐了，
that still might leak some information.
这仍然可能会泄露一些信息。
But that's kind of a we can kick down the road and probabilistically not
但这是一种我们可以拖延下去的事情，从概率上来说不会
going to happen if you require passwords of sufficiently long length, most
发生，如果你要求密码足够长，大多数
likely.
可能。
So any questions on salting, which to be clear,
所以，关于加盐，说清楚一点，
is just a mechanism for decreasing the probability
只是一个降低概率的机制，
that an adversary is going to glean information
对手获取信息的概率
that you might not want them to have?
你可能不希望他们拥有的信息？
So what does this mean concretely?
那么，这在具体上意味着什么？
When you get an email from a website saying "click this link
当你收到来自网站的电子邮件说 "点击此链接
to reset your password," it's not the website, if well designed,
重置你的密码"，如果网站设计良好，就不是网站，
is being difficult or shy and not telling you your password,
很难或害羞，不告诉你你的密码，
the web administrators just do not know, ideally, your password.
理想情况下，网站管理员根本不知道你的密码。
So what are they doing?
那么他们在做什么呢？
They're probably sending you a link, similar in spirit
他们可能正在给你发送一个链接，在精神上类似
to a one-time password, there's some random unique string in there
于一次性密码，里面有一些随机的唯一字符串，
that's unique to you.
那是你独有的。
They've stored that in their database.
他们已经将它存储在他们的数据库中。
So as soon as you click on that link, they check their database
所以，当你点击那个链接时，他们会查看他们的数据库
and be like, oh, wait a minute, I know I set this link a minute ago to David.
然后就会说，哦，等等，我知道我几分钟前将这个链接设置给了 David。
Let me just trust now-- because probabilistically there's no way
让我现在就信任一下，因为从概率上来说，不可能
someone guessed this URL within 60 seconds--
有人能在 60 秒内猜到这个 URL。
let's trust that whatever he wants to type in as his new password
让我们相信，无论他想要输入什么作为他的新密码
should be associated with that Malan account in the database.
都应该与数据库中的那个 Malan 账户关联。
But if, conversely, you ever get an email saying your password is 123456
但是，反过来，如果你曾经收到过一封电子邮件，说你的密码是 123456
or whatever it is, it is clearly not being hashed, let alone salted,
或任何其他密码，它显然没有被哈希，更不用说加盐了，
on the server.
在服务器上。
And that is not a website to do anything particularly sensitive with.
那不是一个可以做任何特别敏感事情的网站。
All right, so what more can we do?
好的，那么我们还能做什么呢？
Well, let's pick up where we left off in week two on the art of cryptography,
好吧，让我们从第二周关于密码术的艺术中继续，
this art, the science of scrambling information, but in a reversible way.
这种艺术，对信息进行加密的科学，但它是可逆的。
So whereas hashing, as we've described it here, is really tends to be one-way,
所以，就像我们在这里描述的那样，哈希实际上倾向于单向，
whereby you should not be able to reverse the process unless you cheat
除非你作弊，否则你应该无法逆转这个过程，
and make a massive table of all of the inputs
并制作一个包含所有输入的大型表格，
and all of the outputs, which isn't really so much
以及所有输出，这不像真正的
reversing as it is just looking it up.
逆转，而是查找它。
Cryptography, like in week 2, can actually
密码学，就像在第二周一样，实际上
be a solution to a lot of problems, not just sending messages
可以解决很多问题，不仅仅是发送信息
across a crowded room.
穿过拥挤的房间。
We, weeks ago, really focused on this type of cryptography
几周前，我们真正关注这种类型的密码学，
whereby you've got some plain text message.
你有明文信息。
You've got a key, like a secret number 1 or 13 or something else.
你有一个密钥，就像一个秘密数字 1 或 13 或其他东西。
The cipher, which might be a rotational cipher or a substitution cipher,
密码，可能是轮转密码或替换密码，
some algorithm, and then ciphertext was the term
某些算法，然后密文是描述加密版本的术语。
of art for describing the scrambled version.
艺术。
That should look like random zeros and ones or letters
它应该看起来像随机的 0 和 1 或字母
of the alphabet or the like.
或类似的东西。
This though was reversible, whereby you could just
不过，它是可逆的，你可以直接
input the ciphertext with the key and get back out the plain text.
输入密文和密钥，并得到明文。
Maybe you have to change a positive number to a negative number.
可能你需要将一个正数改为负数。
But the key is really the same.
但密钥实际上是相同的。
Be it plus 1 minus 1 or plus 13 minus 13, the process was symmetric.
无论是加 1 减 1 还是加 13 减 13，这个过程都是对称的。
And, indeed, what we talked about in week two
实际上，我们在第二周讨论的是
was an example of something called secret key cryptography, where
称为对称密钥密码学的东西的例子，在那里
there's, indeed, one secret between two parties, a.k.a.
确实，两个参与方之间有一个秘密，也就是
symmetric cryptography.
对称密码学。
Because encryption is pretty much the same as decryption, but maybe
因为加密和解密几乎相同，但可能
you change the sign on the key itself.
你需要改变密钥本身的符号。
But this is not necessarily all we want.
但这不是我们想要的全部。
Because here's that general process.
因为这是通用的过程。
Here's the letter A. Here's the key of 1.
这是字母 A，这是密钥 1。
We outputed in week 2 a value of B. That's not necessarily
我们在第二周输出的值是 B，这并不一定是
the solution to all of our problems.
所有问题的解决方案。
Why?
为什么？
Well, if two people want to communicate securely, they need some shared secret.
好吧，如果两个人想要安全地交流，他们需要一些共同的秘密。
So, for instance, if I wanted to send a secret message to Rongxin
所以，例如，如果我想给 Rongxin 发送一条秘密信息，
in the back of the room here, he and I have better
在房间的后面，我和他事先就达成了一致。
agreed upon a secret in advance.
我们事先就达成了一致。
Otherwise, how can I possibly send a message, encrypt it in a way
否则，我怎么才能发送一条消息，并以一种方式对其进行加密
that he can reverse?
他能逆转？
I mean, I could be like, (WHISPERING) let's use a key of 1.
我的意思是，我可以说，（低声）让我们使用一个密钥为 1。
(SPEAKING NORMALLY) But obviously, anyone in the middle
（正常说话）但显然，中间的任何人
has just now heard that.
刚刚就听到了。
So we might as well not communicate securely at all.
所以我们最好不要进行安全的通信。
So there's this kind of chicken-and-the-egg problem,
所以存在着这样的一个先有鸡还是先有蛋的问题，
not just contrived here in lecture.
这不仅仅是在课堂上编造的。
But the first time I want to buy something on amazon.com
但当我第一次想在 amazon.com 上买东西的时候
with my credit card, I would like my credit card to be encrypted,
用我的信用卡，我希望我的信用卡被加密，
scrambled somehow.
以某种方式被混淆。
But I don't know anyone personally at amazon.com, let alone someone
但我并不认识 amazon.com 的任何人，更不用说
that I've prearranged some secret for my Mac and their servers.
我事先为我的 Mac 和他们的服务器预先安排了一些秘密。
So it seems that we fundamentally can't use symmetric cryptography
所以看来我们不能从根本上使用对称加密
all of the time, unless we have some other mechanism for securely generating
一直使用，除非我们有其他机制来安全地生成
that key, which we don't have as the common case in the world today.
那个密钥，而我们现在还没有像当今世界普遍存在的那样。
Thankfully, mathematicians years ago came up
值得庆幸的是，几年前的数学家就想出了
with something known as asymmetric cryptography, which
一种被称为非对称加密的东西，它
does not require that you use the same secret in both directions.
不需要你在两个方向上使用相同的密钥。
This is otherwise known as public key cryptography.
这也被称为公钥加密。
And it works essentially as follows.
它的工作原理基本上如下。
When you want to take some plaintext message and encrypt it,
当你想取一些明文消息并对其进行加密时，
you use the recipient's public key.
你使用接收者的公钥。
So if Rongxin is my colleague in back and he has a public key,
所以如果荣鑫是我的同事，他有一个公钥，
it is public by definition.
根据定义，它是公开的。
He can literally shout for the whole room
他可以大声地喊，让整个房间
to hear what his public key is, which effectively is just
听到他的公钥是什么，它实际上就是
some big, seemingly random number.
一个大而看似随机的数字。
But there's some mathematical significance of it.
但它有一些数学意义。
And I can write that down.
我可以把它写下来。
Heck, you can all write it down if you too want to send him secure messages.
哎呀，如果你想给他发送安全消息，你们都可以写下来。
And out of those two inputs, we get one output, the ciphertext,
从这两个输入中，我们得到一个输出，即密文，
that I can then hand off to people in the room in those virtual envelopes.
然后我可以把它交给房间里的人，放在那些虚拟信封里。
And it doesn't matter if all of you have heard his public key.
而且，你们是否听到过他的公钥并不重要。
Because you can perhaps guess where this is going.
因为你可能猜到这将走向何方。
How would Rongxin reverse this process?
荣鑫将如何逆转这个过程？
He's not going to use one public key.
他不会使用一个公钥。
He's going to use, not surprisingly, a corresponding private key.
不出所料，他将使用一个相应的私钥。
And so in asymmetric cryptography or public key cryptography,
因此，在非对称加密或公钥加密中，
you really have a key pair, a public key and a private key.
你实际上拥有一对密钥，一个公钥和一个私钥。
And for our mathematical purposes today, let
为了我们今天数学上的目的，让我们
me just stipulate that there's some fancy math involved, such
规定，其中涉及一些复杂的数学，例如
that when you choose that key or, really, those keys,
当你选择那个密钥，或者实际上是那些密钥时，
there's a mathematical relationship between them.
它们之间存在着数学关系。
And knowing one does not really give you any information about the other.
而知道一个并不能真正告诉你关于另一个的任何信息。
Why?
为什么？
Because these numbers are so darn big it would take adversaries more
因为这些数字非常大，敌对方需要更多的时间
time than we all have on Earth to figure out via brute force
比我们所有人在地球上的时间还要多，才能通过暴力破解的方式
what the corresponding private key is.
找出相应的私钥。
The math is that good.
数学就是这么好。
And even as computers get faster, we just
即使计算机越来越快，我们也只是一直
keep using bigger and bigger keys, more and more bits
使用越来越大的密钥，越来越多的位
to make the math even harder for adversaries.
让敌对方更难进行数学运算。
So when Rongxin receives that message, he uses his private key,
所以当荣鑫收到那条消息时，他使用他的私钥，
takes the ciphertext I sent him through the room,
取回我通过房间发送给他的密文，
and gets back out the plaintext.
并得到明文。
So this is exactly how HTTPS works effectively
所以这正是 HTTPS 如何有效地工作的
to securely establish a channel between me and Amazon.com, gmail.com.
来在我和 Amazon.com、gmail.com 之间安全地建立一个通道。
Any website starting with https:// uses public key cryptography to come up
任何以 https:// 开头的网站都使用公钥加密来
with, initially, a secret.
产生一个最初的密钥。
And in practice, it turns out, mathematically,
在实践中，从数学上讲，
it's faster to use secret key crypto.
使用密钥加密速度更快。
So very often, people will use asymmetric crypto
所以，人们经常使用非对称加密
to generate a big shared key and then use the faster algorithms thereafter.
来生成一个大的共享密钥，然后使用更快的算法。
But it does solve asymmetric cryptography,
但它确实解决了非对称加密，
that chicken-and-the-egg problem, by giving us all public keys and private
那个先有鸡还是先有蛋的问题，通过为我们提供所有公钥和私钥
keys.
密钥。
If you've heard of RSA, Diffie-Hellman, elliptic curve cryptography,
如果你听说过 RSA、Diffie-Hellman、椭圆曲线加密，
there's different algorithms for this that you can actually
有不同的算法，你实际上可以
study in higher level, more theoretical classes.
在更高级、更理论的课程中学习。
But there's a bunch of different ways mathematically to solve this problem.
但从数学上讲，有很多不同的方法来解决这个问题。
But those are the primitives involved.
但那些是所涉及的原始概念。
And how many of you have heard of now passkeys, which
你们中有多少人听说过现在的通行证，它
is kind of only just catching on in recent months, literally.
实际上，最近几个月才开始流行起来。
If I had to make any prediction this semester,
如果我必须在本学期做出任何预测，
odds are, you're going to see these in more and more places.
很有可能，你会在越来越多的场合看到它们。
And in fact, the next time you register for a website or log into a website,
事实上，下次你注册网站或登录网站时，
look for a link, a button that maybe doesn't say passkeys, per se.
寻找一个链接，一个按钮，它可能不叫通行证，而是叫别的东西。
It's often called passwordless login.
它通常被称为无密码登录。
But it's really referring to the same thing.
但这实际上指的是同一件事。
Passkeys are essentially a newish feature of operating systems,
通行证本质上是操作系统的一种新功能，
be it Mac OS or Windows or Linux or the OS running on your phone,
无论是 Mac OS、Windows、Linux 还是手机上的操作系统，
that doesn't require that you choose a username and password anymore.
它不再要求你选择用户名和密码。
Rather, when you visit a website for the very first time,
相反，当你第一次访问一个网站时，
your device will generate a public and private key pair.
你的设备将生成一对公钥和私钥。
Your device will then send to the website for what
你的设备会将你的公钥发送给网站，以便它拥有其中一个值，
you're registering your public key so that it has one of the values,
但你保留你的私钥，确实是私有的。
but you keep your private key, indeed, private.
And using the same mathematical process that I alluded to earlier,
使用我和之前提到的相同的数学过程，
you can therefore log into that website in the future
因此，将来你可以登录该网站
by proving mathematically that you are, in fact, the owner
通过数学证明你确实是所有者
of the corresponding private key.
对应的私钥
So, in essence, if we use a picture like this,
所以，本质上，如果我们使用这样的图片
when you proceed to log in to that website again-- and, again,
当你再次登录该网站时，再次
that website has stored your public key--
该网站存储了你的公钥
it essentially uses something known as digital signatures--
它本质上使用了一种称为数字签名的技术
you're familiar with this term, you've heard it in the wild--
你熟悉这个词，你曾在现实中听说过
whereby the website will send you a challenge message,
该网站会向你发送一条挑战信息
like some random number or string of text.
比如一个随机数或一段文本
It's just some random value.
它只是一个随机值
If you then effectively encrypt it with your private key or run both of those
然后，你用你的私钥加密它，或者将两者都运行
through a particular algorithm, you'll get back a signature.
通过特定的算法，你将获得一个签名
And that signature can be verified by the website by using your public key.
该网站可以使用你的公钥来验证该签名
So digital signatures are kind of an application of cryptography
所以，数字签名是密码学的一种应用
but in the reverse direction.
但是方向相反
In the world of encryption, you use someone's public key
在加密的世界里，你使用某人的公钥
to send a message encrypted.
发送加密的信息
And they use their private key to decrypt it.
他们使用自己的私钥来解密它
In the world of signatures, or really passkeys,
在签名的世界里，或者说是密钥的世界里
you reverse the process, whereby you use your private key to effectively encrypt
你颠倒了这个过程，你使用你的私钥来加密
some random challenge you've been sent.
你收到的随机挑战
And the website, the third party, can use your public key
该网站，第三方，可以使用你的公钥
to verify, OK, mathematically, that response came from David.
验证，好的，从数学上来说，这个回复来自大卫
Because I have his public key on file.
因为我有他的公钥
So what's the upside of this?
那么，这样做有什么好处呢？
We just get out of the business of passwords and password managers
我们就可以摆脱密码和密码管理器的烦恼
more generally.
更普遍地说
You do have to trust and protect your devices, be it
你确实需要信任和保护你的设备，无论是
your phone or your laptop or desktop all the more.
你的手机，你的笔记本电脑，还是你的台式机
And that's going to open another possible threat.
这将带来另一种潜在的威胁
But this is a way to chip away at what is becoming the reality
但这是一种方法，可以逐渐摆脱我们正在面临的现实
that you and I probably have dozens, hundreds of usernames and passwords
你和我都可能拥有几十个，甚至几百个用户名和密码
that's probably not sustainable long-term.
从长远来看，这可能无法持续下去
And, indeed, we read to often about hacks in the wild as a result.
事实上，我们经常看到有关网络攻击的报道
Questions then on cryptography or passkeys?
那么，关于密码学或密钥还有问题吗？
All right, just a few more building blocks to equip you for the real world
好的，让我们再学习几个构建块，让你在现实世界中游刃有余
before we sort of maybe do a final check for understanding of sorts.
在我们进行最终的理解检查之前
So when it comes to encryption, we can solve other problems as well.
所以，谈到加密，我们还可以解决其他问题
And in this too is a feature you should increasingly be seeking out.
这也有一个功能，你应该越来越重视它
So end-to-end encryption refers to a stronger use of encryption
端到端加密指的是一种更强大的加密方式
than most websites are actually in the habit of using.
比大多数网站实际使用的加密方式更强大
Case in point, if you're using HTTPS to send an email to Gmail,
举个例子，如果你使用 HTTPS 发送电子邮件到 Gmail
that's good because no one between you and Gmail servers
这是好的，因为你与 Gmail 服务器之间
presumably can see the message because it's encrypted.
没有人可以看到邮件内容，因为它被加密了
It just looks like random zeros and ones.
它看起来只是一堆随机的 0 和 1
So it's effectively secure from people on the internet.
所以，它实际上可以防止网络上的人窥探
The emails are not secure from like nosy employees at Google
但是，这些电子邮件无法防止 Google 好奇的员工窥探
who do have access to those servers.
他们确实可以访问这些服务器
Now, maybe through corporate policy, they shouldn't or physically don't.
当然，也许由于公司政策，他们不应该，或者实际上也不能访问
But, theoretically, there's someone at Google
但是，理论上，Google 的某个员工
who could look at all of your email if they were so inclined.
如果他们愿意，就可以查看你所有的电子邮件
Hopefully it's just not a long list of people.
希望这只是个小范围的人
But end-to-end encryption ensures that if you're
但是，端到端加密确保，如果你
sending a message from A to B, even if it's going through C in the middle--
从 A 发送信息到 B，即使它经过了中间的 C
be it Google or Microsoft or someone else-- end-to-end encryption
无论是 Google，还是 Microsoft，或者其他人，端到端加密
means that you're encrypting it between A and B. And so even C in the middle
意味着你在 A 和 B 之间加密信息。因此，即使是中间的 C
has no idea what's going on.
也不知道发生了什么
This is not true of services like Gmail or Outlook.
像 Gmail 或者 Outlook 这样的服务就不是这样
This is true of services like iMessage or WhatsApp
像 iMessage 或者 WhatsApp 这样的服务就是这样的
or Signal or Telegram or other services where if you poke around, also
或者 Signal，Telegram，或者其他类似的服务，如果你仔细研究，你也会看到
you'll see literally mention of end-to-end encryption.
明确地提到了端到端加密
It's a feature that's becoming a little more commonplace,
这是一个越来越普遍的功能
but something you should seek out when you don't necessarily trust or want
但是，当你不想信任中间的设备时，你应该寻找这个功能
to trust the machine in the middle, the point
不想信任中间的设备，也就是
C between A and B. So, indeed, when sending messages on phones
A 和 B 之间的 C。所以，确实，当你用手机发送信息时
and even video conferencing nowadays too.
甚至现在进行视频会议时也是如此
And here's something where sometimes you kind of have to dig.
有些时候，你需要深入挖掘
Most of us are familiar with Zoom certainly by now.
我们大多数人现在肯定都熟悉 Zoom 了
And if we go into Zoom settings, which I did
如果你打开 Zoom 的设置，我今天早上也这样做了
this morning to take this screenshot, this is what it looks like as of now.
拍下了这个截图，目前它看起来是这样的
Here's the menu of options for creating a new meeting.
这是创建新会议的选项菜单
And toward the bottom here-- it's a little small--
在底部，字体比较小
you'll notice that you have two options for encryption.
你会注意到你有两种加密选项
And funny, enough the one that's typically selected
有趣的是，默认情况下选择的
by default, unless you opt in to the other one, is enhanced encryption.
选项，除非你选择另一个，是增强加密
Brilliant marketing, right?
营销策略很厉害，对吧？
Who doesn't want enhanced encryption.
谁不想要增强加密呢？
It is weaker than this encryption though, which is end-to-end encryption.
但是，它比这种加密更弱，这种加密是端到端加密
End-to-end encryption means that when you're
端到端加密意味着，当你
having a video conference with one or more people,
和一个或多个其他人进行视频会议时
not even Zoom can see or hear what you're talking about.
即使是 Zoom 也看不到，也听不到你们在说什么
Enhanced encryption means no one between you
增强加密意味着，你
and Zoom can hear or see what you're talking about.
与 Zoom 之间没有人能听到或看到你们在说什么
So end-to-end ensures that it's A to B, and if Zoom is C In the story,
所以，端到端加密确保信息从 A 传递到 B，如果 Zoom 是故事中的 C
even Zoom can't see what you're doing.
即使是 Zoom 也看不到你们在做什么
Now, there are some downsides.
当然，也有一些缺点
And there's some little fine print here.
这里有一些细则
When you enable end-to-end encryption on a cloud-based service like Zoom,
当你启用像 Zoom 这样的云服务上的端到端加密时
you can't use cloud recordings anymore.
你不能再使用云录制了。
Why?
为什么？
Well, if Zoom by definition mathematically
嗯，如果Zoom从定义上来说，在数学上
can't see or hear your meeting, how are they going to record it for you?
无法看到或听到你的会议，他们怎么能为你录制呢？
It's just random zeros and ones.
它只是随机的0和1。
You can still record it locally on your Mac or PC,
你仍然可以在你的Mac或PC上本地录制，
but end-to-end encryption ensures that you
但端到端加密确保了你
don't have to worry about prying eyes-- be it a company, be it a government,
不必担心窥视的眼睛——无论是公司、政府，
a state more generally.
或者更普遍地说，一个国家。
And so societally, you'll start to see this discussed probably even
因此在社会上，你会看到这可能比现在更频繁地被讨论
more than it already is when it comes to personal liberties and freedom
当涉及到个人自由的时候，比现在还要多。
among citizens of countries and states because
因为这是国家和地区公民的自由。
of the implications for actual privacy that these primitives
因为这些基本原理对实际隐私的影响
that we've been discussing and that you even explored in week 2,
我们一直在讨论，你甚至在第二周探索了，
albeit weakly, with these ciphers we used in the real world.
尽管很弱，但我们使用了这些我们在现实世界中使用的密码。
But encryption has one other use that's worth knowing about too and yet
但加密还有另一个值得了解的用途，同时
another feature to turn on.
还有一个功能可以开启。
So when it comes to deleting files, odds are, most everyone in the room
所以当谈到删除文件时，很有可能，房间里的大多数人
knows on a Mac or PC that when you drag a file to the trashcan or the recycle
都知道在Mac或PC上，当你把文件拖到垃圾桶或回收站时
bin, it doesn't actually go away unless you right click
里，它实际上不会消失，除非你右键点击
or Control click or go to the appropriate menu and empty the trash.
或Ctrl点击或进入相应的菜单并清空垃圾桶。
But did anyone know that even when you empty the trash or recycle bin,
但有人知道即使你清空了垃圾桶或回收站，
the file also doesn't really go away.
该文件实际上并没有消失。
Your operating system typically just forgets where it is.
你的操作系统通常只是忘记了它在哪里。
But the zeros and ones that compose the file or files you tried to delete
但是组成你试图删除的文件的0和1
are still there for the pickings, especially
仍然存在，尤其
if someone gets physical or virtual access to your system.
如果有人获得了你系统的物理或虚拟访问权限。
So, for instance, here is a whole bunch of ones and zeros.
例如，这里有一堆0和1。
Maybe it's representing something on my hard drive.
也许它代表着我的硬盘上的某些东西。
And suppose that I want to go ahead and delete
假设我想删除
a file that comprises these zeros and ones, these bits here.
包含这些0和1的文件，这些位。
Well, when your operating system deletes the file,
那么，当你的操作系统删除文件时，
even if you click on Empty Trash or Empty Recycle Bin,
即使你点击清空垃圾桶或清空回收站，
it essentially just forgets about those bits, but doesn't actually change them.
它本质上只是忘记了这些位，但并没有真正改变它们。
Only once you create a new file or download something else
只有当你创建一个新文件或下载其他东西时
do some of those zeros and ones end up getting overwritten.
这些0和1中的一些才会被覆盖。
And per the yellow remnants here, the implication of this contrived example
根据这里的黄色残余，这个编造的例子所暗示的是
is that even at this point in time you can still recover
即使在此时此刻，你仍然可以恢复
like half of the file, it would seem.
似乎有一半的文件。
So maybe the juicy part with a credit card number
所以也许是包含信用卡号码的那部分
or a message that you really wanted to delete or the like, there's
或者是你真的想删除的信息，或者类似的东西，还有
still remnants on the computer's hard drive here.
计算机硬盘上的残余。
So what's the alternative?
那么有什么替代方案呢？
Well, if you really want to be thorough, you
如果你真的想彻底一点，你可以
could delete files and then download the biggest possible movies you
删除文件，然后下载你能下载的最大的电影
can to really fill up your hard drive.
来填满你的硬盘。
Because, probabilistically, you would end up
因为，从概率上来说，你最终会
overwriting all of those zeros and ones eventually.
最终覆盖掉所有的0和1。
But that's not really a tenable solution.
但这并不是一个可行的解决方案。
It would just take too much time and it's
这将花费太多时间，而且
fraught with possible simple mistakes.
很容易犯一些简单的错误。
So what should we do instead, well, maybe we
那么我们应该怎么做呢？也许我们
should securely delete information.
应该安全地删除信息。
And securely delete would mean when you actually
而安全地删除意味着当你真正地
empty the recycle bin or the trash can, what happens to the original zeros
清空了回收站或垃圾桶，原始的0和1会发生什么
and ones is that you take them and you change all of them
和1，你将它们拿走，把它们都
to zeros or all of them to ones or all of them to random zeros and ones.
变成0，或者全部变成1，或者全部变成随机的0和1。
Why?
为什么？
So that you can still reuse those bits now,
这样你就可以重新使用这些位了，
but there's no remnants even on the computer's hard drive
但即使在计算机的硬盘上，也没有任何残余
that they were once there.
表明它们曾经存在过。
But even now, this is not fully robust.
但即使现在，这也不是完全健壮的。
Why?
为什么？
It turns out that because of today's electronics and solid state devices,
事实证明，由于当今的电子产品和固态设备，
there might still be remnants of files on them because these hard drives,
它们上面可能仍然存在文件残余，因为这些硬盘，
these storage devices nowadays are smart enough
现在的存储设备足够智能
that if they realize that parts of them are failing,
如果它们意识到它们的部分正在失效，
they might prevent you from changing data in certain corners.
它们可能会阻止你在某些角落修改数据。
So if you think of your memory as like a big rectangle, some of the bits
所以如果你把你的内存想象成一个大矩形，一些位
might get blocked off to you just over time.
可能会随着时间的推移而被屏蔽掉。
So there might still be remnants there.
所以可能仍然存在残余。
So if you really are worried about a sibling, an employer, or a government
所以如果你真的担心你的兄弟姐妹、雇主或政府
like finding data on that system, there might actually still be remnants.
能够在该系统上找到数据，实际上可能仍然存在残余。
Now, you can go extreme and just physically
现在，你可以采取极端措施，直接物理地
destroy the device, which should be pretty effective.
销毁设备，这应该非常有效。
But that's going to get pretty expensive over time when you want to delete data.
但当你想要删除数据时，随着时间的推移，这会变得非常昂贵。
Or, again, we can use encryption as the solution to this problem.
或者，我们再次可以使用加密作为这个问题的解决方案。
So, again, encryption is increasingly in the real world
所以，再次强调，加密在现实世界中越来越
an amazing tool for your toolkit because it can be deployed in different ways.
成为你工具箱中的一款神奇工具，因为它可以以不同的方式部署。
So, in this case, full disk encryption is something
所以，在这种情况下，全盘加密是一个
you can enable in Windows or Mac OS.
你可以在Windows或Mac OS中启用。
Nowadays, it's typically enabled by default on iOS
如今，它通常在iOS上默认启用
and you can opt in as well on other platforms.
你也可以在其他平台上选择加入。
In the world of full disk encryption, instead of storing any of your files
在全盘加密的世界里，你不再将你的任何文件存储为
as a plain text, like in their original raw format,
纯文本，就像它们原始的格式一样，
you essentially randomize everything on the disk instead.
你本质上是将磁盘上的所有内容随机化。
You rely on the user's password or some unique string
你依赖于用户密码或他们知道的某些唯一字符串
that they know when you log into your Mac or PC
当你登录你的Mac或PC时。
to essentially scramble the entire contents of the hard drive.
来对硬盘的整个内容进行加密。
And it's not quite as simple as that.
而且情况并不像看起来那么简单。
Typically, there's a much larger key that's
通常，有一个更大的密钥
used that in turn is protected by your actual password.
被使用，而它又受到你实际密码的保护。
But, in this case, this means that if someone steals your laptop while you're
但，在这种情况下，这意味着如果有人在你
not paying attention in Starbucks or the airport or even your dorm room,
没有注意的情况下，在星巴克或机场，甚至在你的宿舍里，
even if they open the lid and don't have your password,
即使他们打开盖子，没有你的密码，
they're not going to be able to access any of the data
他们将无法访问任何数据
because it's just going to look like zeros and ones.
因为它看起来就像零和一。
Even if they remove the hard drive from your device,
即使他们从你的设备上拆下硬盘，
plug it into another device, they're only going to see zeros and ones.
把它插到另一个设备上，他们也只能看到零和一。
Now, if you walk away from your laptop at Starbucks with the lid open
现在，如果你在星巴克把笔记本电脑的盖子打开就离开了
and you're logged in, there is a window of opportunity.
并且你已经登录，就会有一段可乘之机。
Because the data has got to be decrypted when you care about it and when
因为当你在乎数据的时候，当你使用数据的时候，它必须被解密。
you're using it.
你在使用它。
So here too is another example of best practice.
所以这里也是另一个最佳实践的例子。
You should minimally be closing the lid of your laptop,
你至少应该把笔记本电脑的盖子关上，
making sure it's logging you out or at least locking the screen,
确保它把你注销，或者至少锁住屏幕，
so that someone can't just walk off with your device
这样别人就无法拿着你的设备走掉
and have access to your logged in account.
并且访问你的已登录账户。
But full disk encryption essentially decreases the probability
但全盘加密本质上降低了
that an adversary is going to be successful.
攻击者成功的可能性。
In the world of Macs, it's called FileVault.
在 Mac 世界中，它被称为 FileVault。
It's in your System Preferences.
它在你的系统偏好设置里。
Windows, it's called BitLocker.
Windows 中，它被称为 BitLocker。
There's third party solutions too.
也有第三方解决方案。
Here too, we have to trust that Microsoft and Apple don't
在这里，我们也要相信微软和苹果不会
screw up and write buggy code.
出错并写出有错误的代码。
But generally speaking, turning on features like these things
但总的来说，开启像这些功能
are good for you.
对你来说是有好处的。
Except what's maybe an obvious downside of doing this?
除了可能的一个明显的缺点？
What's that?
是什么？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众： [听不见]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, if you forget your password.
大卫·马兰：是的，如果你忘记了密码。
There's no mathematician in the world who
世界上没有哪个数学家
is probably going to be able to recover your data for you.
可能能够帮你恢复数据。
So there too, it's maybe a hefty tradeoff.
所以，这也是一个相当大的权衡。
But hopefully you have enough defenses in place,
但希望你有足够的防御措施，
be it your-- a good password, a password manager,
无论是你的——一个好的密码，一个密码管理器，
maybe even printing out your primary password on a sheet of paper,
也许甚至把你的主要密码打印在一张纸上，
but locking it in a box or bringing it home so that no one near you
但把它锁在一个盒子里，或者带回家，这样你身边的人
actually has physical access, you can at least mitigate some of these risks.
实际上无法接触到它，你至少可以减轻一些这些风险。
You'll read about, though, in the real world even this,
不过，你会在现实世界中读到，即使是这个，
which is like an adversarial use of full disk encryption.
这就像对全盘加密的对抗性使用。
Sometimes when hackers get into systems, this
有时当黑客进入系统时，这
has happened literally with hospital systems, municipal government systems,
已经发生在医院系统、市政政府系统，
and the like.
等等。
If they hack into them, they don't just delete the data or just create havoc,
如果他们入侵了它们，他们不仅会删除数据，或者制造混乱，
they will proactively encrypt the server's hard drive
他们会主动地用一个只有黑客知道的随机密钥加密服务器的硬盘
with some random key that only the hacker knows.
用一个只有黑客知道的随机密钥加密服务器的硬盘。
They will then demand that the hospital or the town
然后他们会要求医院或城镇
pay them, often in Bitcoin or some cryptocurrency
付钱给他们，通常是比特币或其他加密货币
to decrease the probability of being caught,
以降低被抓到的可能性，
and they'll only turn over that key to decrypt the data if someone actually
而且他们只有在有人实际
pays up.
付钱的时候才会交出那个密钥来解密数据。
So here too, there's sort of a dark side of these mathematical principles.
所以，这些数学原理也有一面黑暗的一面。
So there too, it's always a trade off between good people and perhaps bad.
所以，这也永远是好人与坏人之间的权衡。
Well, maybe before we wrap and before we serve
好吧，在我们结束之前，在我们提供之前
some cake in the transept, Carter, can you join me one last time?
一些蛋糕在耳堂里，卡特，你能最后一次加入我吗？
But, first, before I turn things over to me and Carter, here's your problem
但是，首先，在我把事情交给我和卡特之前，这是你的问题
set 10, a sort of unofficial homework.
集 10，一个非正式的家庭作业。
One, among your takeaways for today, you should
一、你今天应该记住的一点是，你应该
start using a password manager or even these fancier passkeys, at least
开始使用密码管理器，甚至这些更高级的通行证，至少
for your most sensitive accounts.
用于你最敏感的账户。
So anything medical, financial, particularly personal,
所以任何医疗、金融、特别是个人方面的，
like this is a very concrete takeaway and action item.
就像这是一个非常具体的收获和行动项目。
I wouldn't sit down and try to change all of your accounts over.
我不会坐下来尝试更改你所有的账户。
Because knowing humans, You're not going to get through the whole to-do list.
因为了解人类，你不会完成整个待办事项列表。
So maybe do it the next time you log into that account,
所以，也许下次你登录那个账户的时候，
turn on some of these features or add it to a password manager
打开一些这些功能，或者添加到密码管理器中
or at least start with the most important.
或者至少从最重要的开始。
Two, turning on two-factor authentication
二、开启双重身份验证
beyond where you have to at places like Harvard and Yale,
超出你在哈佛和耶鲁等地方必须做的事情，
but certainly bank accounts, privates, anything medical, personal,
但当然，银行账户、私人信息、任何医疗、个人方面的信息，
or the like.
等等。
And then lastly, where you can, turning on end-to-end encryption.
最后，在你可以的地方，开启端到端加密。
Being careful with it, you don't want to go
小心点，你不想
and during lecture, hopefully no one clicked the turn on FileVault button
在讲座期间，希望没有人点击了开启 FileVault 按钮
while we're in class.
在我们上课的时候。
Because closing your laptop lid while things are being encrypted
因为在加密的时候关闭笔记本电脑的盖子
is generally bad practice.
通常是不好的做法。
See us after though if you did do that a moment ago.
不过，如果你刚才做到了，请事后来找我们。
So here's just then three actionable takeaways.
所以，这里就是三个可以操作的收获。
But we thought we'd conclude by taking a few final minutes for a CS50 quiz
但我们想用最后几分钟来做 CS50 的小测验
show of sorts, a final check for understanding using some questions
作为一种展示，使用一些问题来最终检验理解
we come up with ourselves, but also some of the review questions
我们自己想出来的，也有一些复习题
that you all kindly contributed as part of the most recent problem set.
你们大家作为最近一次作业的一部分，很乐意贡献。
So some of these questions come from you yourselves.
所以，这些问题中有一些来自你们自己。
And let me go ahead and turn things over to Carter here to help run the show.
让我把事情交给卡特，让他来主持节目。
We will invite you at this point to take out that same device
现在，我们邀请你拿出那台设备
as you had earlier.
和你之前一样。
This is the same URL as before.
这是和之前一样的 URL。
But if you closed the tab, you can reopen it here.
但是如果你关闭了标签页，你可以在此处重新打开。
To make things a little fun-- because we still have some cookies
为了让事情更有趣 - 因为我们还有饼干
left-- could we get three final CS50 volunteers?
剩下 - 我们能再找三位 CS50 志愿者吗？
OK, one hand is already up.
好，已经有一只手举起来了。
How about two hands there?
那里还有两只手吗？
And how about three hands?
还有三只手吗？
Over here.
这边。
All right, yes, sure, a round of applause for our final volunteers.
好的，当然，让我们为最后三位志愿者鼓掌。
Come on up.
请上来。
[APPLAUSE]
[鼓掌]
On the line are some delicious Oreo cookies.
线上有一些美味的奥利奥饼干。
If the three of you would like to come over and take
如果你三位想过来，并从
any of these seats in the middle, you will be our human players,
中间的座位上选择任何一个，你将成为我们的真人玩家，
but we'll invite everyone in the group to play too.
但我们也会邀请小组里的每个人一起玩。
Do you want to take a mic and introduce yourself to the world?
你想拿个麦克风，向世界介绍一下自己吗？
AUDIENCE: Sure.
观众：当然。
Hi, I'm Dani.
嗨，我是丹妮。
I'm a first year in WIG C. And I'm planning on studying economics.
我是 WIG C 的一年级学生，我计划学习经济学。
DAVID MALAN: Nice, welcome.
大卫·马兰：很好，欢迎。
AUDIENCE: Hi, I'm Rochelle.
观众：嗨，我是罗谢尔。
I'm from the best state, Ohio.
我来自最好的州，俄亥俄州。
DAVID MALAN: [INAUDIBLE]
大卫·马兰：[听不清]
AUDIENCE: And I'm a freshman in Greeno.
观众：我是一名格林诺大学的 freshman。
I'm planning on concentrating in CS.
我计划主修 CS。
DAVID MALAN: Nice, welcome.
大卫·马兰：很好，欢迎。
And?
还有呢？
AUDIENCE: My name is Jackson.
观众：我叫杰克逊。
I'm from Indiana.
我来自印第安纳州。
I live in Thayer.
我住在塞耶。
I'm a first year.
我是一年级学生。
And I'm studying linguistics and Germanic languages and literatures.
我学习语言学和日耳曼语文学。
DAVID MALAN: Welcome as well.
大卫·马兰：也欢迎你。
So, if our volunteers could have a seat, you're
所以，如果我们的志愿者能坐下来，你们
going to want to be able to see this screen or that one.
要能看到这个屏幕或那个屏幕。
So you can move your chairs if you would like.
所以，如果你想的话，可以移动你的椅子。
Carter is going to kindly cue up the software, which hopefully everyone
卡特将很乐意启动软件，希望每个人
has on their phones as well.
也都在他们的手机上安装了。
And I should have mentioned, do you have your phone with you?
我应该早点说，你带手机了吗？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Do you have your phone with you?
大卫·马兰：你带手机了吗？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: OK, do you have your phone over there?
大卫·马兰：好的，你那边有手机吗？
OK, what's your name again?
好的，你叫什么名字来着？
AUDIENCE: Rochelle.
观众：罗谢尔。
DAVID MALAN: OK, Rochelle will be right back,
大卫·马兰：好的，罗谢尔马上回来，
if you want to go grab your phones.
如果你想拿一下手机的话。
And in the meantime, we're going to go ahead and-- thank
同时，我们要开始 - 感谢
you so much-- we're going to go ahead and cue up the screens here
你们 - 我们要开始启动这里的屏幕
for the CS50 quiz show.
为 CS50 知识问答节目。
It's about 20 questions in total, the first few of which
总共有大约 20 道题，其中前几道
are going to focus on cybersecurity to see how well we
将会集中在网络安全上，看看我们
can check our current understanding.
对当前的理解程度如何。
The rest will be questions written by you in the days leading up to today.
剩下的问题是你们在今天之前几天里写出来的。
All right, Carter, let's go ahead and reveal the first question.
好的，卡特，让我们开始揭示第一个问题。
And note that you can win up to 1,000 points this time per question.
请注意，这次每道题最多可以获得 1000 分。
It's not just about being right or wrong.
这不仅仅是关于对错。
And you get more points the faster you buzz in as well.
你抢答得越快，得分也越高。
So we'll see who's on the top based on all of the guest user names.
所以我们会根据所有客人的用户名，看看谁排在第一。
All right, here we go, Carter, question one,
好的，卡特，开始吧，第一题，
what is the best way to create a password?
创建密码的最佳方法是什么？
Substitute letters with numbers or punctuation signs,
用数字或标点符号替换字母，
ensure it's at least eight characters long,
确保它至少有八个字符，
have a password manager generated for you,
让密码管理器为你生成，
or include both lowercase and uppercase letters?
还是同时包含小写字母和大写字母？
All right, let's see what the results are.
好的，让我们看看结果吧。
Almost everyone said have a password manager generate it for you.
几乎所有人都说让密码管理器为你生成。
90% of you said that's the case.
你们中有 90% 都这么认为。
And, indeed, that one is correct.
的确，那个是正确的。
Nicely done.
做得很好。
Let's go ahead and see the random usernames you've chosen.
让我们来看看你们选择的随机用户名。
So this looks like it's web_hexidecimalidentifier to keep
看起来像是 web_hexidecimalidentifier，用来保持
things anonymous.
匿名。
So if you are OAF9E, nicely done, but there's
所以，如果你叫 OAF9E，做得很好，但现在
a whole lot of ties up at the top.
很多人都并列第一。
All right, and I see-- well, just to keep things interesting,
好的，我看到 - 好吧，为了让事情更有趣，
you had 792 points.
你得了 792 分。
You had--
你得了 -
AUDIENCE: 917.
观众：917 分。
DAVID MALAN: 917 points, 917 points.
大卫·马兰：917 分，917 分。
So it's a close race here.
所以现在比分很接近。
Number two, what is a downside of two-factor authentication?
第二题，双重身份验证的缺点是什么？
You might lose access to the second factor.
你可能会失去对第二个因素的访问权限。
Your account becomes too secure.
你的账户变得过于安全。
You can be notified someone else is trying to access your account.
你可以收到通知，有人试图访问你的账户。
You can pick any authentication you like.
你可以选择任何你喜欢的验证方式。
Hopefully, you can reload.
希望你能重新加载。
You might have missed that one.
你可能错过了那个。
And the number one answer was might lose access to the second factor.
而最常选的答案是，你可能会失去对第二个因素的访问权限。
Indeed, 93% of you got that.
的确，你们中有 93% 都选对了。
And we're up to 1,375 points, 792 points, and--
现在分数分别是 1375 分，792 分，还有 -
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: OK, and forced reload.
大卫·马兰：好的，强行重新加载。
So, yes, you tried reloading the page and hopefully it'll click back in.
所以，是的，你尝试重新加载页面，希望它能恢复正常。
All right, Carter, number 3.
好的，卡特，第三题。
We have, what would you see if you tried to read an encrypted disk?
如果尝试读取一个加密的磁盘，你会看到什么？
You would see a random sequence of zeros and ones,
你会看到一堆随机的 0 和 1，
scrambled words from the user's documents,
用户文档中的乱码，
all of the user's information, or all one's?
用户的所有信息，还是全是 1？
About 10 seconds remain.
还剩大约 10 秒。
Is it working for you now?
现在可以了吗？
OK.
好的。
All right, three seconds.
好的，三秒钟。
And the ranked answers are a random sequence of zeros and ones.
排名答案是零和一的随机序列。
91% of you indeed got that right.
你们中有 91% 的人确实答对了。
Let's see who's winning on the guest screen.
让我们看看谁在嘉宾屏幕上获胜。
Web user a28c3, nicely done.
网络用户 a28c3，做得很好。
But it's still a close tie among three of you anonymous participants.
但你们三个匿名参与者仍然势均力敌。
Number four, which type of encryption is most secure--
第四题，哪种类型的加密最安全？
enhanced encryption, end-to-end encryption, full scale encryption,
增强型加密、端到端加密、全面加密、
advanced encryption?
高级加密？
About five seconds.
大约五秒钟。
And most popular response is the correct one, end-to-end encryption
最受欢迎的答案也是正确的，端到端加密
with 92% of you.
你们中有 92% 的人选择了它。
Nice.
不错。
We're up to 2,375, 3,792, and 2,917.
现在是 2,375 分、3,792 分和 2,917 分。
And good job to these three folks in the front of our list.
恭喜这三个人在我们榜单的前列。
All right, Carter, number 5, the last on cybersecurity.
好的，Carter，第五题，关于网络安全的最后一题。
When would it make sense to store your password on a sticky note
什么时候在你的电脑旁放一张便签纸来记录你的密码是有意义的？
by your computer?
在你的电脑旁？
When it's too complicated to remember, when
当它太复杂而记不住的时候，当
you need to access your account quickly, when you share your account with family
你需要快速访问你的账户的时候，当你与家人分享你的账户的时候
members, never.
成员，永远不会。
Oh.
哦。
And the most popular response was never, which is indeed correct.
最受欢迎的答案是永远不会，这确实是对的。
And only 79% of you think that right now.
而只有 79% 的人现在认为是正确的。
It is never OK to store it on a post-it note on your computer.
在你的电脑上用便签纸记录密码永远不可取。
You should minimally be using today's password manager for that same process.
至少应该使用当今的密码管理器来完成这个过程。
All right, two of you, a28c3 and c9a23 are still atop the list.
好的，你们两个人，a28c3 和 c9a23 仍然在榜首。
We have 3,000-plus points, 3,000-plus points,
我们有超过 3,000 分，超过 3,000 分，
and probably about the same as well.
可能也差不多。
All right, now we move on to the user-generated content
好的，现在我们进入你们大家从哈佛和耶鲁大学为我们生成的用户的生成内容
that you all from Harvard and Yale generated for us.
部分。
Number 6, what is the variable type that stores true/false values?
第六题，存储真/假值的变量类型是什么？
Boolean, string, integer, or double?
布尔型、字符串型、整型还是双精度型？
About 10 seconds to come up with this.
大约 10 秒钟来想出这个答案。
We saw these in different languages, these types.
我们在不同的语言中看到了这些类型。
But the idea was the same.
但想法是一样的。
And in two seconds, we'll see that the answer
两秒钟后，我们会看到答案
is Boolean with 96% response rate.
是布尔型，回答率为 96%。
All right, what else do we have here?
好的，这里还有其他什么？
It's still a two-way tie at the top.
榜首仍然是两强争霸。
All right, next question, Carter, is number 7.
好的，下一题，Carter，第七题。
What placeholder would you use when trying
当你试图在 C 语言中
to print a float in C, a float in C?
打印一个浮点数时，你会使用什么占位符？
Seven seconds.
七秒钟。
I'll defer to the visual syntax on the screen for this one.
这个我会让屏幕上的可视语法来解释。
And the most popular and correct answer is, indeed, %f.
最受欢迎的答案也是正确的答案，确实是 %f。
We never saw %fl and we definitely didn't see %float.
我们从来没有见过 %fl，当然也没有见过 %float。
Two of you, though, are still in the lead.
不过，你们两个人仍然领先。
Nicely done, whoever you are.
做得很好，无论你是谁。
All right, next question, what does I++ do in C++ where I is an integer value?
好的，下一题，在 C++ 中 I++ 的作用是什么，其中 I 是一个整数值？
Note, for the record, we did not teach C++ in this course,
注意，为了记录，我们在这门课程中没有教授 C++，
but this question is from you.
但这个问题是你们提出来的。
I will admit it's the same as in C, which we did teach.
我承认它和 C 语言中的作用一样，我们确实教授过 C 语言。
Decrements the integer, deletes the integer, increments the integer by one,
减少整数值、删除整数值、将整数值增加 1、
or reassigns the integer to zero?
还是将整数值重新设置为零？
The most popular answer and correct answer
最受欢迎的答案也是正确的答案
is increments the integer by one.
是将整数值增加 1。
It definitely doesn't decrement, so.
它肯定不会减小，所以。
All right, two responses still atop the list.
好的，两个答案仍然在榜首。
And here we have 6,000-plus, 6,000, and 6,000.
这里有超过 6,000 分、6,000 分和 6,000 分。
So it's getting closer.
所以越来越接近了。
Using a hash table to retrieve data is useful
使用哈希表检索数据很有用
because it theoretically achieves a search time of O of n, O of n log n,
因为它理论上可以实现 O(n) 的搜索时间、O(n log n) 的搜索时间、
O of log n, or O of 1?
O(log n) 的搜索时间还是 O(1) 的搜索时间？
Five seconds to make your decision.
还有 5 秒钟做出你的决定。
Getting a little harder.
越来越难了。
And let's see the results.
让我们看看结果。
O of 1, only 30% of you got the correct answer from a very core week 5 topic.
只有 30% 的人答对了这道非常重要的第五周的题目，正确答案是 O(1)。
That is the theoretical hope of a hash table.
那是哈希表的理论期望。
In practice, though, to be fair, it can devolve, as we saw, into O of n.
然而，公平地说，在实际应用中，它可能会退化成 O(n)，就像我们之前看到的那样。
We didn't really see those other two answers in the context of hash tables
我们并没有真正看到其他两个答案在哈希表的语境中
specifically.
出现过。
All right, wow, a28c3 is in the lead now.
好的，哇，a28c3 现在领先了。
Let's take a look at number 10, halfway there.
我们来看看第十题，已经过半了。
What is the first program we made in CS50?
我们在 CS50 中做的第一个程序是什么？
This should be fast.
这应该很快。
All right, Greet, Meow, DNA, Hello, world?
好的，Greet、Meow、DNA、Hello, world？
One second.
一秒钟。
And it was, indeed, Hello, world, Hello, world.
确实，是 Hello, world，Hello, world。
All right, still in the lead with 10,000 points.
好的，仍然领先，得分 10,000 分。
And now let's move on to the second half.
现在让我们进入下半场。
Question 11, when malloc is used to allocate memory in a C program,
第十一题，当在 C 程序中使用 malloc 为内存分配空间时，
that memory is allocated in the pile, heap, bin, or stack?
该内存是在堆、堆、池还是栈中分配的？
Very creative set of answers.
一组非常有创意的答案。
Five seconds.
五秒钟。
All right, and the results have heap at 43%.
好的，结果显示堆的得票率为 43%。
Malloc was from the heap at the top.
Malloc 是从最上面的堆分配的。
The stack is where function calls go.
栈是存放函数调用的地方。
It's getting a little more worrisome here.
这里有点令人担忧了。
But that's OK.
但没关系。
Still in the lead with perfect score, it seems, 11,000 points.
似乎仍然领先，得分 11,000 分，是满分。
Next up is number 12.
接下来是第十二题。
Which data structure allows you to change its size dynamically and store
哪种数据结构允许你动态地改变其大小，并在
values in different areas of the memory--
内存的不同区域存储值？
an array, a queue, a linked list, or a stack?
数组、队列、链表还是栈？
Change its size dynamically and store different values
动态地改变其大小，并在内存的不同区域存储不同的值。
in different areas of the memory.
。
And the answer from the group is a linked list at 62%, which is correct.
组里给出的答案是链表，得票率为 62%，这是正确的。
An array, as we defined it, cannot be resized.
正如我们所定义的，数组不能改变大小。
You can create a new array, copy everything over.
你可以创建一个新的数组，并将所有东西复制过来。
I'm starting to think maybe we shouldn't end the class on this note.
我开始觉得也许我们不应该以这种方式结束课程。
But that's OK.
但没关系。
We'll move on.
我们继续吧。
12,000 points for the lead.
领先者获得12000分。
And number 13, what does CSS stand for in web development--
第13题，在网页开发中，CSS代表什么？
computer style sheets, cascading style sheets, creative style systems,
电脑样式表，层叠样式表，创意样式系统，
colorful sheets styles?
彩色样式表？
And most popular answer is correct with 81%, cascading style sheets.
最受欢迎的答案是正确的，获得了81%的支持，层叠样式表。
On the top 10 list here at 1,300 points, still a perfect score,
在排行榜的前十名中，1300分，仍然是满分，
and our three human volunteers are doing well here too.
我们的三个志愿者也做得很好。
14, how to represent a decimal number 5 in binary.
第14题，如何用二进制表示十进制数5。
All right, here we go.
好了，我们开始吧。
I'll let you read these.
我让你读一下这些。
All rights, fingers crossed, decimal number 5 in binary is, indeed, 101.
好的，希望一切顺利，十进制数5的二进制表示确实是101。
Because that's a 4 plus 0 plus 1 gives us a decimal 5.
因为4加0加1等于十进制数5。
All right, next question, and amazing a28c3, whoever you are out there,
好了，下一题，还有a28c3，无论你是谁，
nicely done.
做得很好。
Who is the CS50 mascot--
CS50的吉祥物是谁？
cat, duck, robot dog Spot, Oscar the Grouch?
猫，鸭子，机器狗Spot，奥斯卡·怪人？
All of whom have appeared in some form.
他们都以某种形式出现过。
This one will be a little looser with answers, but looks like duck and cat
这题答案会稍微宽松一些，但看起来鸭子和猫
were both the most popular.
都是最受欢迎的。
Duck has kind of become the mascot, suffice it to say.
可以说，鸭子已经成为了吉祥物。
Cat is kind of everywhere on CS50 social media.
猫在CS50的社交媒体上随处可见。
So we'll accept cat as well.
所以我们也接受猫。
We love Spot, but has only made that one appearance.
我们喜欢Spot，但它只出现过一次。
15,000.
15000。
Final few questions, what is the output of printf quote, unquote, "1" plus
最后几个问题，printf "1" 加上
quote, unquote, "2?"
"2" 的输出是什么？
It will return an error, twelve, 3, or 12?
它会返回错误、twelve、3还是12？
English and digits respectively there.
英文和数字分别表示。
Six seconds.
六秒钟。
All right, one second.
好了，一秒钟。
And 12 with 74% is correct.
12获得了74%的支持，是正确的。
Because it's not quite 12, it is more rather
因为这不是真正的12，更准确地说，
1, 2 because those are two strings that got concatenated would not actually
1，2，因为它们是两个被连接起来的字符串，实际上
be an error in that case.
不会产生错误。
It's just not what you expect.
只是不像你预期的那样。
All right, it's getting a little harder, but still someone's
好了，越来越难了，但仍然有人
got a perfect score.
获得了满分。
What does LIFO stand for?
LIFO代表什么？
Lost In First Order, Last In First Out, Let Inside Fall Outside,
迷失在第一顺序中，后进先出，让内部掉到外面，
Long Indentation For Organization?
长的缩进用于组织？
Good one.
不错。
Last In First Out, and we discussed this in the context of a stack.
后进先出，我们在堆栈的背景下讨论过这个。
Because as you pile things on top of the stack,
因为当你把东西堆放在堆栈顶端时，
the last one in is the first one out.
最后一个进来的第一个出去。
All right, nicely done, this player here.
好的，这位玩家做得很好。
Three questions to go.
还剩三个问题。
On average, how early did you submit the weekly pset?
平均而言，你提前多长时间提交了每周的作业？
A couple of days early, no rush, the morning of, a couple of hours early,
提前几天，不着急，早上，提前几个小时，
but was not too nervous, 11:59:59, I live on the edge.
但并不太紧张，11:59:59，我活在边缘。
Again, user-generated content.
再次，用户生成的内容。
And the most popular answer--
最受欢迎的答案是
[LAUGHTER] Carter and I conferred before class
[笑声] 卡特和我上课前商量了一下
and we autocratically decreed that this is
我们专断地宣布，这就是
the only right answer and the only one we
唯一正确的答案，也是我们唯一
will accept here, though we appreciate the others as well.
接受的答案，尽管我们也感谢其他答案。
Wow, all right, did you take this class for the CS50 shirt?
哇，好的，你是为了CS50的T恤才来上这门课的吗？
Yes, no, maybe, I'm not telling you?
是的，不，也许，我不告诉你？
So that is this here shirt, which you'll get at the CS50 fair.
所以就是这件T恤，你将在CS50嘉年华上获得它。
One second.
等一下。
And, yes, no, maybe, I'm not telling you, this time, we'll accept all four
还有，是的，不，也许，我不告诉你，这次，我们接受这四个
of those, which brings us to our final question, at which point
中的所有答案，这将我们引向最后一个问题，到那时
we'll reveal the scores of all of our participants
我们将公布所有参与者的分数
and see if we can get the number one score online.
并看看我们是否能获得网上排名第一的分数。
What is the phrase that David says at the end of each lecture?
大卫在每次讲座结束时会说些什么？
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
[插话声]
DAVID MALAN: All right, before we actually
DAVID MALAN：好的，在我们实际
say what the right answer is, though we can show it,
说出正确答案之前，尽管我们可以展示它，
Carter, we'll see that there is 98%--
卡特，我们会看到有98%的人——
I've never said this at the end here, but 98% answers there.
我从未在结尾说过这句话，但98%的人回答正确。
Let's go ahead and look at the top chart.
让我们看一下排行榜。
Do we know who web_a28c3 is?
我们知道web_a28c3是谁吗？
Oh my goodness, come on down.
天啊，快下来。
And among our friends here, can you pull up each of your scores
还有我们这边的朋友们，你能把你们的分数都调出来吗？
if you're able to see?
如果你能看到的话？
And among our human volunteers, 16,792, 17,292, 16,958.
在我们的志愿者中，16792，17292，16958。
So we have our human winner as well.
所以我们也有了人类的获胜者。
So without further ado, allow me to thank our volunteers.
因此，不多说，请允许我感谢我们的志愿者。
Thanks so much to CS50 staff.
非常感谢CS50的工作人员。
We're about to give out some cookies and, if you want,
我们马上要分发一些曲奇饼，如果你想的话，
some stress balls here.
这里还有一些减压球。
Cake is now served.
蛋糕现在上桌了。
And this was CS50.
这就是CS50。
[CHEERING]
[欢呼声]
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
[插话声]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]